<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <id>https://bread.codes/</id>
    <title>BreadCodes</title>
    <updated>2026-01-22T02:47:05.227Z</updated>
    <generator>feed</generator>
    <author>
        <name>BreadCodes</name>
        <email>brad@bread.codes</email>
        <uri>https://bread.codes/about</uri>
    </author>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://bread.codes/"/>
    <link rel="self" href="https://bread.codes/atom"/>
    <subtitle>code stuff</subtitle>
    <logo>https://bread.codes/image.png</logo>
    <icon>https://bread.codes/favicon.ico</icon>
    <rights>All rights reserved 2025, BreadCodes</rights>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Chapter 1: Intro to Butano]]></title>
        <id>butano-series-1</id>
        <link href="https://bread.codes/posts/butano-series-1"/>
        <updated>2026-01-18T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[In this chapter, we will introduce Butano, a modern C++ high-level engine for Game Boy Advance homebrew development, and set up our development environment.]]></summary>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<center>
  <a href="https://buymeacoffee.com/breadcodes" target="_blank">
    <img src="/assets/buymeacoffee.png" alt="Buy Me A Coffee" style="width: 200px;" />
  </a>
</center>

## Getting Started

### Prerequisites

While I will be doing all of my development on MacOS and Linux, DevKitPro supports Windows as well. You can find installation instructions for all three platforms on the [DevKitPro website](https://devkitpro.org/wiki/Getting_Started).

#### Software

##### Development Tools

- [DevKitPro](https://devkitpro.org/wiki/Getting_Started), our toolchain for building GBA homebrew
  - Once installed, install the `gba-dev` package.
    - Windows:
        This is done through the GUI installer. Choose the `gba-dev` package from the list. If you forgot to install it, you can re-run the installer to add it
    - MacOS / Linux terminal:
      - Most systems: `dkp-pacman -S gba-dev`
      - Some distros using vanilla pacman: `pacman -S gba-dev`
- [mGBA](https://mgba.io/downloads.html), an emulator for testing our GBA homebrew.
  - Supports GDB debugging as well for breakpoints and memory inspection.
- `git`, for version control
  - Windows: [Git for Windows](https://gitforwindows.org/)
    - For the remainder of this tutorial, you will be using the Git Bash terminal so that the commands match those shown for MacOS and Linux.
  - MacOS: Install via [Homebrew](https://brew.sh/) with `brew install git`, or download from [git-scm.com](https://git-scm.com/download/mac)
  - Linux: Install via your package manager, e.g. `sudo apt install git` on Debian-based systems

Some flavorful alternatives for the experienced reader who wants to explore beyond the scope of this tutorial:

- Toolchains:
  - [Wonderful Toolchain](https://wonderful.asie.pl/), an alternative GBA homebrew toolchain supported by Butano.
    - For Windows & Linux only!
- Emulators:
  - [VisualBoyAdvance-M (VBA-M)](https://github.com/visualboyadvance-m/visualboyadvance-m), a popular alternative emulator for GBA homebrew development.
    - It supports debugging with gdb like mGBA, which is very useful
  - [Mesen](https://mesen.ca/), an alternative emulator that supports GBA, has a color mode that more closely matches the original screen, and has a great debugger.

Finally, you will need a code editor. This is the most highly subjective part of the setup, so I will leave it up to you. 

If you are a beginner, don't use a basic text editor or an IDE that requires extensive configuration unless you really know what you're doing. Beginners will fall into the trap of simple text editors or misconfigurations, and run into errors they don't know how to debug. IDEs are designed to help you with debugging and code management. Experienced developers may prefer text editors or highly configurable IDEs, but they also know how to debug issues that arise from using them.

I have included configurations for the following editors in the repository:

|**Editor**|**Pros**|**Cons**|**Notes**|
|:---:|:---:|:---:|:---:|
|[Visual Studio Code](https://code.visualstudio.com/)|Supports every OS<br/>Free and open source<br/>Extensive plugin ecosystem<br/>Supports many languages and frameworks<br/>Supports GDB debugging with the right extensions<br/>Integrated git support|Can be resource-intensive with many extensions<br/>Built on Electron and Chromium, which comes with its own set of trade-offs|Popular choice|
|[Zed](https://zed.dev/)|Free and open source<br/>Fast and modern features<br/>Built on Rust for memory safety<br/>Good language support<br/>Integrated git support|Newer IDE with a smaller ecosystem|I like it a lot. I use it for my job.|
|Any editor that uses clangd for C++ language server support|Clangd provides smart code analysis, autocompletion, and error checking|Requires configuration to set up clangd and integrate with the editor|Flexible option for advanced users|

Editors that I recommend but did not include configurations for:

|**Editor**|**Pros**|**Cons**|**Notes**|
|:---:|:---:|:---:|:---:|
|[CLion](https://www.jetbrains.com/clion/)|First-class C++ support with smart code analysis<br/>Integrated debugger<br/>Great refactoring tools|Paid product (free trial and free licenses for students and open source contributors)<br/>More resource-intensive than VS Code|My preferred IDE for C++ development|
|[Visual Studio](https://visualstudio.microsoft.com/)|Powerful IDE with extensive features<br/>Excellent debugging and profiling tools<br/>Strong C++ support|Primarily Windows-focused<br/>Can be resource-intensive|Great for Windows users|
|[Vim / Neovim](https://neovim.io/)|Extremely lightweight and fast<br/>Highly customizable with plugins<br/>Powerful keyboard-centric editing|Steeper learning curve<br/>Requires configuration for optimal C++ support|Great for those who prefer terminal-based editors|

##### Art Tools

\* What we will be using in this series.

- Visual Asset Options:
  - [Aseprite (paid)](https://www.aseprite.org/)\*, a pixel art tool for creating sprites and animations.
    - Paid software, but worth the investment. I have bought this software 3 times across different computers because I use it so much.
  - [Aseprite (source)](https://github.com/aseprite/aseprite/releases), the open source version of Aseprite that you can compile yourself.
    - Lacks some features of the paid version, but still very capable.
  - [GIMP](https://www.gimp.org/), a free and open source image editor.
    - More general-purpose than Aseprite, but can be used for pixel art as well.
  - [Krita](https://krita.org/en/), another free and open source image editor.
    - Also more general-purpose, but has good support for pixel art.

- Audio Assets Options:
  - [OpenMPT](https://openmpt.org/)\*, a free and open source tracker for creating music.
    - Supports exporting to formats compatible with GBA homebrew.
    - Windows "only" software, but can be run on MacOS & Linux with Wine (requires `wine`).
      - MacOS
        - Install [Homebrew](https://brew.sh/) if you haven't already with `/bin/bash -c "$(curl -fsSL https://raw.githubusercontent.com/Homebrew/install/HEAD/install.sh)"`
        - Run `brew install --cask wine-stable` to install Wine.
      - Linux
        - Install Wine via your package manager, e.g. `sudo apt install wine` on Debian-based systems.
  - [Furnace Tracker](https://tildearrow.org/furnace/), a free and open source tracker designed for chiptune music.
    - Cross-platform and lightweight.
    - "Supports" making GBA music, but the only format it can export that is compatible is VGM, which means you can only make Game Boy / Color music. Luckily, the GBA is backwards compatible with GB/C audio, but you cannot take advantage of the GBA's 2 PCM channels.
      - This could be a misunderstanding on my part; please correct me if I'm wrong!

### Getting the starter repository

From here on out, if you are on Windows, "terminal" means the Git-Bash terminal. It is important to use Git-Bash because many commands will not work correctly in Command Prompt or PowerShell.

Open your terminal, navigate to your desired directory, and run the following commands to clone the starter repository and navigate into it:

```bash
# Clone the repository and navigate into it
git clone https://github.com/breadbored/butano-tutorial-series.git butano-tutorial-series
cd butano-tutorial-series

# Initialize git submodules, which includes Butano itself and an extension for Fonts
git submodule update --init --recursive
```

In this directory you will find:

```text
butano-tutorial-series/
├─ chapter-1-getting-started/   - Our starting point for this series
├─ .gitignore
├─ LICENSE
├─ README.md
```

You can follow along with the tutorial series in its entirety by using the `chapter-1-getting-started` directory as your starting point, and work in that directory (or copy that directory elsewhere) for the duration of the series. The other directories are provided for reference. For the purposes of this tutorial, we will be working in the `chapter-1-getting-started` directory.

```bash
cd chapter-1-getting-started
```

Now let's build and run our starter project to ensure everything is working correctly.

```bash
make
```

To start the game in mGBA (without debugging with gdb) you can run:

```bash
make run
```

Once you see the mGBA window pop up with our starter project running, congratulations! Your development environment is set up correctly!

### What's Next?

Next we will begin working with assets in Butano. This includes creating and importing sprites, backgrounds, and audio into our project. We will also explore ways to use those assets.

### Chapter Overview

###### ButanoSeriesNav "1","1"

---
---

### Communities

#### Discord

- Please remember this is ***not my server***, so do not dominate the conversation with questions about this series. The topics are more broad than this series or even Butano itself, so please be respectful of that.
- If you need help, the thing that helps everyone involved is providing your full source code, or if you are unwilling to do that, a "Minimally Reproducible Example" that demonstrates your issue. Not only might you find your problem along the way, but this is a good practice in general when asking for help with programming.
- Please be respectful to @GValiente, the author of Butano, as well as other ***volunteers*** who are ***volunteering*** their time to help you. You are not entitled to their time or labor. I have had people break this rule ***many*** times in ***many*** projects. This is a hobby for everyone involved.
- Please search the channels for your question before asking it. Chances are, someone else has had the same question before you.
- Follow the server rules.

[![Discord](https://img.shields.io/badge/Discord-%235865F2.svg?style=for-the-badge&logo=discord&logoColor=white)](https://discord.gg/ctGSNxRkg2)

#### Reddit

[r/Homebrew](https://www.reddit.com/r/Homebrew/) - A general homebrew community for all consoles.
[r/RetroGameDev](https://www.reddit.com/r/RetroGameDev/) - A community for retro game development, including homebrew.

#### BSky

[@Bread.Codes](https://bsky.app/profile/bread.codes) - My Bluesky profile. Many of the people I follow are into homebrew and retro game development.

#### Support the Community

Want there to be Jams? Want more resources, tutorials, and tools? Support the community by donating to the [OpenCollective](https://opencollective.com/gbadev) for GBADev! Your donations help fund events like [GBAGameJam](https://itch.io/jam/gbagamejam) and support the work of volunteers who create tools and resources for the community.

[![OpenCollective](https://img.shields.io/badge/Support-GBADev-blue?style=for-the-badge&logo=opencollective&logoColor=white)](https://opencollective.com/gbadev)


---

### Support the Series

<center>
  <a href="https://buymeacoffee.com/breadcodes" target="_blank">
    <img src="/assets/buymeacoffee.png" alt="Buy Me A Coffee" style="width: 200px;" />
  </a>
</center>

---

### License

This series is licensed under a [Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International License](https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/).

The purpose of this license is to allow you to share this series freely, as long as you attribute BreadCodes as the original author, and do not commercialize the content through paid courses, books, or other means.

The project repository for this series is almost entirely licensed under the same license. The exception is `chapter-1-getting-started/LICENSE`, which is licensed under the [MIT License](https://opensource.org/licenses/MIT) to allow for more flexibility when using the starter code for your own projects. This project uses 3rd party assets which may have different licenses; please refer to the `LICENSE` file in that directory for more information.
]]></content>
        <author>
            <name>BreadCodes</name>
            <email>brad@bread.codes</email>
            <uri>https://bread.codes/about</uri>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Chapter 0: Introductions and Overview]]></title>
        <id>butano-series-0</id>
        <link href="https://bread.codes/posts/butano-series-0"/>
        <updated>2026-01-16T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[In this chapter, we will introduce the Butano series, outline what we will be building, and provide an overview of the Butano engine.]]></summary>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<center>
  <a href="https://buymeacoffee.com/breadcodes" target="_blank">
    <img src="/assets/buymeacoffee.png" alt="Buy Me A Coffee" style="width: 200px;" />
  </a>
</center>

## Preface

Welcome to my tutorial series on Butano, a modern C++ high-level engine for Game Boy Advance homebrew development. This will begin with introductions, then getting our environment setup, and then we will move into building a simple game over the course of several chapters.

If you'd like to skip introductions and get straight to the setup, you can jump to [Chapter 1](/posts/butano-series-1).

### About Me

My name is Brad, aka "Bread" (as the baristas at coffee shops often call me). I am a hobbyist of many things. Professionally I am a Lead Data Engineer, though most of my experience was in Backend Software Engineering and Database Administration. My favorite language overall is SQL, because I love data transformation and declarative puzzles. My favorite imperative language is probably Rust, though there's such a small gap between Rust and C++ that it's hard to say definitively.

18 years ago I was gifted Mario Galaxy for the Nintendo Wii, and I was so blown away by the physics of a planetary system that 11 year old me wanted ***nothing*** more than to do that myself. Not just on PC, but on the Wii itself. I remember the day I published my first project for PC: March 14th 2009. My goal was always homebrew for consoles, but I wouldn't start seriously pursing that as my primary hobby until around COVID-19 in 2020.

### Intended Audience

While I will try to keep things as beginner-friendly as possible, I will be writing for an audience that has at least a basic understanding of C++ and minimal game development concepts. Butano is less of a game engine and more of a framework for asset management. As you'll come to find in this series, Butano simplifies most - but not all - aspects of developing a game for the Game Boy Advance.

This is intended for people who are interested in the hobby and it is supposed to be a fun use of your time. This series is for people who are driven by the high of making cool stuff.

Game Dev - and especially Homebrew Game Dev - is largely art, so I want to make this clear sooner rather than later: the use of GenAI tools is discouraged. I know people - including myself - are opinionated on the subject. The use of GenAI is not allowed in GBA Game Jams, and I feel that this is a good standard to uphold for learning and hobby purposes. Not only is this supposed to be fun, but copyright infringement is a valid concern for artists.

### What We Will Be Building

Over the course of this series, we will be building a simple puzzle game based on [Klotski](https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Klotski), which is often referred to as "sliding block puzzle." The goal of the game is to move - as I call it - "inconveniently" arranged rectangular blocks, which impede each other's paths, to free the target block. I recommend [this video](https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=YGLNyHd2w10) about Klotski for a handful of reasons, only one of which is relevant to this series (how the game works). This game will lay a great foundation for understanding Butano's core features, game loops, entity management, collision, and other game development concepts. For Butano specifically, we'll cover the following major features:

- Sprites
  - Regular
  - Affine
  - Fonts
- Backgrounds
  - Regular
  - Affine
  - Tiles
- Inputs
- Audio
  - Music
  - Sound Effects

### Chapter Overview

###### ButanoSeriesNav 0

---

### Communities

#### Discord

- Please remember this is ***not my server***, so do not dominate the conversation with questions about this series. The topics are more broad than this series or even Butano itself, so please be respectful of that.
- If you need help, the thing that helps everyone involved is providing your full source code, or if you are unwilling to do that, a "Minimally Reproducible Example" that demonstrates your issue. Not only might you find your problem along the way, but this is a good practice in general when asking for help with programming.
- Please be respectful to @GValiente, the author of Butano, as well as other ***volunteers*** who are ***volunteering*** their time to help you. You are not entitled to their time or labor. I have had people break this rule ***many*** times in ***many*** projects. This is a hobby for everyone involved.
- Please search the channels for your question before asking it. Chances are, someone else has had the same question before you.
- Follow the server rules.

[![Discord](https://img.shields.io/badge/Discord-%235865F2.svg?style=for-the-badge&logo=discord&logoColor=white)](https://discord.gg/ctGSNxRkg2)

#### Reddit

[r/Homebrew](https://www.reddit.com/r/Homebrew/) - A general homebrew community for all consoles.
[r/RetroGameDev](https://www.reddit.com/r/RetroGameDev/) - A community for retro game development, including homebrew.

#### BSky

[@Bread.Codes](https://bsky.app/profile/bread.codes) - My Bluesky profile. Many of the people I follow are into homebrew and retro game development.

#### Support the Community

Want there to be Jams? Want more resources, tutorials, and tools? Support the community by donating to the [OpenCollective](https://opencollective.com/gbadev) for GBADev! Your donations help fund events like [GBAGameJam](https://itch.io/jam/gbagamejam) and support the work of volunteers who create tools and resources for the community.

[![OpenCollective](https://img.shields.io/badge/Support-GBADev-blue?style=for-the-badge&logo=opencollective&logoColor=white)](https://opencollective.com/gbadev)


---

### Support the Series

<center>
  <a href="https://buymeacoffee.com/breadcodes" target="_blank">
    <img src="/assets/buymeacoffee.png" alt="Buy Me A Coffee" style="width: 200px;" />
  </a>
</center>

---

### License

This series is licensed under a [Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International License](https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/).

The purpose of this license is to allow you to share this series freely, as long as you attribute BreadCodes as the original author, and do not commercialize the content through paid courses, books, or other means.

The project repository for this series is almost entirely licensed under the same license. The exception is `chapter-1-getting-started/LICENSE`, which is licensed under the [MIT License](https://opensource.org/licenses/MIT) to allow for more flexibility when using the starter code for your own projects. This project uses 3rd party assets which may have different licenses; please refer to the `LICENSE` file in that directory for more information.
]]></content>
        <author>
            <name>BreadCodes</name>
            <email>brad@bread.codes</email>
            <uri>https://bread.codes/about</uri>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Release your Album on the Game Boy Advance]]></title>
        <id>release-your-album-on-the-game-boy-advance</id>
        <link href="https://bread.codes/posts/release-your-album-on-the-game-boy-advance"/>
        <updated>2026-01-13T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[Are you a Music-Spreadsheet Wizard?]]></summary>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[Are you a Music-Spreadsheet Wizard?

Do you like your `mod`s and `it`s more than your `wav`s and `mp3`s?

Are you a fan of the limit, as opposed to the limitless?

Today I am introducing a project I've had on my mind for almost a year called TrackPak. TrackPak is a tool that converts your tracker music to an album that runs entirely on the Game Boy Advance.

TrackPak supports several customization options such as fonts, color schemes, and additional details about you and your music.

[Want to try it now?](/album)

## How does it work?

Through the magic of Duct Tape and Prayers™, it's really just two parts:

- A Butano `base/` project that handles the UI and music management
- an Express server that generates a C header for the `base/` project, and starts the `make` process

That's literally it. Due to it's simplicity, I'll be releasing a standalone tool as well in the near future along with the `base/` project that does all the foundational music and UI management.]]></content>
        <author>
            <name>BreadCodes</name>
            <email>brad@bread.codes</email>
            <uri>https://bread.codes/about</uri>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Mario Kart World Toolkit]]></title>
        <id>mario-kart-world-toolkit</id>
        <link href="https://bread.codes/posts/mario-kart-world-toolkit"/>
        <updated>2025-07-19T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[This is a temporary post for hosting the alpha version of the Mario Kart World Toolkit.]]></summary>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[This is a temporary post for hosting the alpha version of the Mario Kart World Toolkit.

Know what to do and just need the download link? [Go here!](#download)

[Join the brand-new Discord](https://discord.gg/FVscyknKZH) for support, feature requests, bug reports, and to contribute art and code!

How to use the Toolkit:

- [Windows 11 24H2, latest update patch](#windows)
    - [Pre-Setup Instructions (Windows 11 24H2 latest patch)](#pre-setup-instructions-windows-11-24h2-latest-patch)
<!-- - [MacOS](#macos)
    - [Pre-Setup Instructions (MacOS)](#pre-setup-instructions-macos)
- [Linux](#linux)
    - [Debian / Ubuntu / Debian-based Distros](#debian-ubuntu-debian-based-distros)
    - [Others](#others) -->
- [Setup Instructions for All Platforms](#setup-instructions-for-all-platforms)
    - [Download](#download)
    - [How to choose a track](#how-to-choose-a-track)
    - [Set up OBS to use the capture card](#set-up-obs-to-use-the-capture-card)
    - [How to test the program for pre-release testing](#how-to-test-the-program-for-pre-release-testing)
- [DISCLAIMER](#disclaimer)

## Windows

### Pre-Setup Instructions (Windows 11 24H2 latest patch)

When I refer to Windows 11, I mean Windows 11 24H2 with the latest updates installed. There is a patch after 24H2 that adds the ability to use the camera in multiple applications at once, which is required for the MKWorld Toolkit to work with OBS.

Instructions with images can be found [here](https://www.elevenforum.com/t/enable-or-disable-multiple-apps-to-use-camera-in-windows-11.31199/).

- Open Windows 11 Settings with `Win + I`.
- Go to "***Bluetooth & devices***"
- Click "***Cameras***"
- Under ***Connected cameras*** , click on the capture card (e.g. "MiraBox") you want to change this setting for.
- Click on the ***Edit*** button for ***Advanced camera options***.
- Turn `on` or `off` ***Allow multiple apps to use camera at the same time*** for what you want, and click on Apply.

[Continue to setup instructions](#setup-instructions-for-all-platforms).

<!-- ## MacOS

### Pre-Setup Instructions (MacOS)

The app is unsigned because an Apple Developer account is $99/year, so you will need to allow the app to run in your security settings.

- Open System Settings.
- Go to "***Privacy & Security***".
- Scroll down to the "***Security***" section.
- Click on the "***Allow***" button next to the "***MKWorld Toolkit*** app.

[Continue to setup instructions](#setup-instructions-for-all-platforms).

## Linux

### Debian / Ubuntu / Debian-based Distros

All good :D

[Continue to setup instructions](#setup-instructions-for-all-platforms).

### Others

Wait until the source is available... I am refactoring the code on a daily basis until I'm happy with architecture, and it is subject to change frequently. I can't reasonably maintain a complex CI/CD pipeline while the code and dependencies are in flux.

[Continue to setup instructions](#setup-instructions-for-all-platforms). -->

---

## Setup Instructions for All Platforms

### Download

- v0.0.5 (latest)
    - [Windows Download](https://github.com/breadbored/breadbored.github.io/releases/download/v0.0.5/MKWorld.Toolkit_0.0.5_x64-setup.exe)
    <!-- - MacOS
        - [Intel/x86_64 Download]()
        - [Apple Silicon/ARM Download]()
    - Linux
        - [Linux (.deb)]() -->
    - Changes:
        - HUGE performance improvements
        - Attempt History and Export
        - Better capture card support
        - 90% of bugs reported have been fixed
- v0.0.4
    - [Windows Download](https://github.com/breadbored/breadbored.github.io/releases/download/v0.0.4/MKWorld.Toolkit_0.0.4_x64-setup.exe)
    - Changes:
        - Added support for Elgato HD60 series capture cards
        - Added support for YUV2 2-byte pixel format
        - Added support for 4k capture cards
- v0.0.3
    - [Windows Download](https://github.com/breadbored/breadbored.github.io/releases/download/v0.0.3/MKWorld.Toolkit_0.0.3_x64-setup.exe)
    - Changes:
        - Added "Data Consent" dialog for optional error reporting
            - This is ***optional*** and ***off by default***, but if enabled, helps me resolve issues in the app faster and easier for everyone. Please consider enabling it.
            - Data is never shared with anyone except me, and is not used for any other purpose.
        - Added support for Windows 11 camera sharing
        - Fixed a bug where all times would report negative if the game pauses
        - Fixed a bug where auto-splits get triggered when the game is paused or the player falls off the track

### How to choose a track

- Click the top left menu button and select "Split Management" in the menu.
- Choose the track you want to run, put in the times you want to compare against, and then click the save button at the very bottom of the screen.

### Set up OBS to use the capture card:

- Open MKWorld Toolkit
- Open OBS and add a new source.
- Choose "Video Capture Device" and select the capture card as the device.
- Add a webview source and set the URL to `http://localhost:2025/obs`.
  - Set the size to 800x1080, or whatever size you want the speedrun split UI to be.
- Arrange to flavor.

### How to test the program for pre-release testing

- Open the MKWorld Toolkit.
- Once MKWorld Toolkit is opened, you can navigate to http://localhost:2025/obs in your web browser.
    - You should now see the speedrun split UI.
- In the MKWorld Toolkit, go to the "Camera Capture" tab if you are not already there.
- Select your capture card and then click the "Start Capture Card" button.
- Play a Time Trial!
    - ***NOTE: If none of the following happens, refresh the http://localhost:2025/obs page in your web browser.***
    - Once the timer in game is detected to be 0:00.000, the timer will reset.
    - Once the race starts, the timer will start counting up.
    - Once a lap is completed, the timer will stop and the splits will be updated.
    - Once the race is completed, the timer will stop and the splits will be updated.
    - The timer resets when you restart the race.

## DISCLAIMER

MKWorld Toolkit is in ALPHA. It was originally built for my own personal use on MacOS, and Windows is in an untested state.]]></content>
        <author>
            <name>BreadCodes</name>
            <email>brad@bread.codes</email>
            <uri>https://bread.codes/about</uri>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Fact Check Movies While Watching]]></title>
        <id>fact-check-movies-while-watching</id>
        <link href="https://bread.codes/posts/fact-check-movies-while-watching"/>
        <updated>2024-10-16T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[Have you ever watched a "Based on a True Story" movie and wondered how much of it was true? Have you ever paused a movie to see how much of it actually happened? Have you heard that American Sniper was mostly fabricated and wanted to know which parts?]]></summary>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[Have you ever watched a "Based on a True Story" movie and wondered how much of it was true? Have you ever paused a movie to see how much of it actually happened? Have you heard that American Sniper was mostly fabricated and wanted to know which parts?

All of those apply to me, and aparently to David McCandless, Dr Stephanie Starling, Omid Kashan, and Karl Webster. They created a [Visualisation of the accuracy of movies "based on a true story"](https://informationisbeautiful.net/visualizations/based-on-a-true-true-story/). 

I felt inspired by their work, and I had an idea: What if we could see fact checking information while watching a movie?... Maybe a bit boring and intrusive to some, but I think this would be a fun feature for those who are interested in the truth behind the stories.

Below are the SRT files for the movies that have been fact checked by the great people I meantioned. I wrote a script to compile into subtitles to be used while watching a movie, and while this post isn't what I have this site for, I thought I'd share the result of a short project instead of the whole process. 

## Download the subtitles:

These subtitles are listed in alphabetical order. You can use these files with your favourite media player that supports SRT files, such as Plex, VLC, Kodi, etc.

- [12 Years a Slave](/assets/factchecksrt/12_years_a_slave.srt)
- [American Sniper](/assets/factchecksrt/american_sniper.srt)
- [Bohemian Rhapsody](/assets/factchecksrt/bohemian_rhapsody.srt)
- [Bridge of Spies](/assets/factchecksrt/bridge_of_spies.srt)
- [Captain Phillips](/assets/factchecksrt/captain_phillips.srt)
- [Dallas Buyers Club](/assets/factchecksrt/dallas_buyers_club.srt)
- [Hacksaw Ridge](/assets/factchecksrt/hacksaw_ridge.srt)
- [Hidden Figures](/assets/factchecksrt/hidden_figures.srt)
- [Lion](/assets/factchecksrt/lion.srt)
- [Philomena](/assets/factchecksrt/philomena.srt)
- [Rush](/assets/factchecksrt/rush.srt)
- [Selma](/assets/factchecksrt/selma.srt)
- [Spotlight](/assets/factchecksrt/spotlight.srt)
- [The Big Short](/assets/factchecksrt/the_big_short.srt)
- [The Imitation Game](/assets/factchecksrt/the_imitation_game.srt)
- [The King's Speech](/assets/factchecksrt/the_kings_speech.srt)
- [The Social Network](/assets/factchecksrt/the_social_network.srt)
- [The Wolf of Wall Street](/assets/factchecksrt/the_wolf_of_wall_street.srt)

## I like this idea, can I submit a movie?

Sure! Email me at [brad@bread.codes](mailto:brad@bread.codes) and I'll send you a tempalte to fill out for your favorite movie, then once you send it back, I'll add it to the list above and credit you and your amazing work. Please include "Fact Check Movie" in the subject line!

## Uh Oh, something's wrong with the subtitles, and it's not just my media player!

If you find an issue with the subtitles like misaligned text, please email me at [brad@bread.codes](mailto:brad@bread.codes) and I'll fix it as soon as possible. Please include "Fact Check Movie" in the subject line!

## How to use the subtitles:

1. Download the SRT file for the movie you want to watch.
2. Open your movie in your favourite media player on your computer (or TV/phone/tablet if you are using Plex, VLC, Kodi).
3. Load the SRT file while the movie is open if you are using VLC. If you are using Plex, you can include the subtitle in the same directory as the movie file, and Plex may automatically load it for you, if not you can choose it in the captions menu.
4. Enjoy the movie with fact checking information!

## Original Data Credits:

Again, thank you so much to David McCandless, Dr Stephanie Starling, Omid Kashan, and Karl Webster for their amazing work. You can find their original visualization [here](https://informationisbeautiful.net/visualizations/based-on-a-true-true-story/).

You can also see their roles and more of their work here:

- Concept & Design: [David McCandless](http://davidmccandless.com)
- Code & Design: [Omid Kashan](https://omid.uk)
- Research: [Dr Stephanie Starling](https://stephaniestarling.com), Karl Webster
- [See the data](https://docs.google.com/spreadsheets/d/1sJDpzYH_sMYuYHqkmZeJGIq_TEXGDjboYdSoew7UjZ8)
- [Information is Beautiful](https://informationisbeautiful.net/)]]></content>
        <author>
            <name>BreadCodes</name>
            <email>brad@bread.codes</email>
            <uri>https://bread.codes/about</uri>
        </author>
    </entry>
</feed>