Original Data Provided By:
Dr Stephanie Starling, David McCandless, DM
Omid Kashan, Karl Webster
Subtitles Compiled By:
BreadCodes
-
TRUE
Northup harvested sugar cane during the periods Epps hired him out. He was good at it.
TRUE-ISH
Northup doesn't specifically mention this, but the slaves at every place Northup worked were closely supervised & often sung as they laboured.
TRUE
The slaves were never afforded a bed or a pillow or any other form of bedding or furniture beyond a rough blanket.
TRUE-ISH
Northup did make several attempts at manufacturing pen & ink from the little he had available. Although he doesn't mention blackberry juice, it's feasible he tried using it as ink.
FALSE
Director & screenwriter made this scene up, stating they 'just wanted a bit of tenderness [...] Then after she's climaxed, she's back where she was. She's back in hell, & that's when she turns & cries.'
TRUE
Northup was a prosperous homeowner with a taste for luxury, so it's likely he had a comfy bed. He was deeply in love with his wife, Anne.
Northup was an accomplished professional violinist.
TRUE
Northup was an accomplished professional violinist. He played regularly at upper-class parties through the winter season.
TRUE-ISH
Northup had 3 children, Elizabeth, 10, Margaret, 8, & Alonzo, 5. Only Margaret & Alonzo make an appearance in the movie. They did have a nice family home.
TRUE
Anne was a successful cook, & during court weeks she was employed as a chef at Sherrill's Coffee House for good money.
The children either went away with Anne or stayed with their aunt while Anne was away.
TRUE-ISH
Mr. Moon was the keeper of a tavern that Northup frequented, & Northup was walking nearby that tavern when he met Hamilton & Brown. However, Northup didn't remember who it was that made the introduction.
TRUE
They told Northup they were entertainers looking for a musician to accompany their shows for 2 weeks en route to Washington. They offered good pay. Northup was excited at the prospect of good money & a trip to the city.
Northup was thrilled by the city & all it had to offer.
TRUE-ISH
Brown & Hamilton had bought liquor for Northup at several establishments throughout the day. The scene where Northup is given $43 & they celebrate their success did happen but it was the previous evening, & was in an apartment, not a restaurant.
TRUE
Hamilton & Brown most likely drugged Northup, rendering him terribly ill. They put him to bed in kind manner. Hours or days later he found himself in chains in a cell, still groggy.
Northup repeated over & over that he was a free man, while Burch insisted he was a Georgia runaway. Burch beat him first with a paddle until it broke, then with a cat o' 9 tails whip, trying to beat a 'confession' out of Northup. It didn't work.
TRUE-ISH
Northup didn't mention this exchange specifically, but they were all given a new set of clothes to keep them looking presentable for buyers.
TRUE
The captives had to sponge off naked in the yard under supervision. Randall cried near constantly for his mother. Radburn made Northup quieten him down, which he did by promising his mama would be there soon.
The 3 of them confided in each other, discussed their options. At this stage Northup was all for plotting, making escape plans. The others were more resigned.
TRUE
Eliza & Emily were added to the group, much to Randall's delight. The 3 of them were incredibly close, & Northup recalls them holding onto each other all day & night.
They were dragged out by night, lined up ready for a journey.
TRUE
They were laid in a flatbed truck & sent to the docks, where they were moved onto a ship.
Ray did advise Northup to stop insisting he was an educated freeman, for it would only earn him trouble. Discovering Robert was in a similar situation to his own, & had been beaten every time he spoke out, Northup resolved to take Ray's advice.
We couldn't find a source for this.
Northup doesn't mention that Robert wore a muzzle.
TRUE-ISH
Northup did discuss the possibility of attacking the crew & escaping, although it was with Robert & another man, Arthur, not with Ray.
FALSE
Robert did die on the ship, but from smallpox. While the rape of female slaves was all too common, Eliza wasn't raped by a sailor on that journey.
TRUE-ISH
Robert's body was thrown overboard, but by one of the sailors. His death put an end to Northup & Robert's escape plot.
FALSE-ISH
On arrival at the dock a man named Arthur, who had been kidnapped, was rescued by his friends. He was overjoyed & ran to them. Since Arthur was omitted from the movie, they seem to have mocked up a similar-ish scene with Ray.
TRUE
There were at least 50 slaves the the dock sitting around ready to be prepped & sold when Northup arrived.
TRUE-ISH
Although the specific trip to Parker's for new luggage shown in the movie wasn't mentioned in the memoir, Northup did write about his family's frequent visits to Parker's for 'articles necessary for my family'.
We couldn't find a source for this.
Northup did shop at Parker's but he didn't write about any incident with a Jasper or Fitzgerald.
TRUE-ISH
Freeman had 'Platt' on his list but nobody had heard of a Platt. Northup had been called 'steward' previously, so while the movie suggests he ignores the call out of pride, he actually just didn't know he was supposed to be Platt. He didn't object to the name.
TRUE
Freeman & his buyers looked over the captives like livestock, slapping their bodies, looking inside their mouths etc., checking their physical strength & soundness.
Freeman carefully arranged his 'stock' in his parlour, lining them up in order of size, placing different groups around the room.
TRUE-ISH
Ford did seek to buy Northup & Eliza, but by this stage Randall was long gone, already sold to another buyer.
TRUE
Randall was made to perform to show his athleticism, & a price was agreed. Eliza screamed & begged not to be separated from her children throughout the sales.
Ford wanted to buy Emily to soothe Eliza, but Freeman refused to sell her, claiming that her beauty & light skin would make her priceless in the years to come. Freeman separated Eliza from Emily by force – a good deal more force than was shown in the film.
TRUE
Ford's new slaves were rested & given food when they arrived. Eliza cried continually for her children.
TRUE-ISH
Although Northup doesn't mention Tibeats singing to them, he was described as a vicious small-minded man. Tibeats & overseer Chapin supervised the slaves.
TRUE
Timber felling & other woodwork was the main job there.
Ford did read passages from the bible to his slaves every Sunday, selecting sections that encouraged kindness toward one another.
TRUE
There was a group of Native Americans settled at the edge of Indian Creek, with whom Northup became friendly & often attended their dances.
TRUE-ISH
This debate did happen, but it wasn't between Tibeats & Northup but between Northup & another man, Adam Taydem, who was Ford's foreman. Ford chose Northup's idea, which pissed Taydem off.
Northup's idea did work well & he was highly commended by Ford, & celebrated by the other slaves. Taydem wasn't impressed.
FALSE
Northup didn't write of Ford giving him a violin, but did write of numerous other kindnesses he offered, including instant forgiveness & care following Northup's escape attempt (not in the movie).
TRUE-ISH
While Northup doesn't mention he & Eliza arguing over her grieving, they did talk about how she suffered. She wept constantly.
TRUE
Ford did read the bible to his slaves, & Eliza pretty much never stopped weeping.
Ford sold Northup to Tibeats. Tibeats was labouring at Ford's at the time, so Northup remained where he was doing the same work, only under a new master. Tibeats constantly antagonised him & was described as cruel & deranged, direspected even by other whites.
TRUE-ISH
Northup didn't see Eliza being dragged away, but she did spend most of her time crying after she was taken from her children. When she became too weak to be useful she was sold. Fully overwhelmed by grief, she stopped eating & drinking & slowly died.
TRUE
Eliza had lived with her previous master, to whom she bore Emily, for 9yrs. He was in love with her & had promised her freedom. He then grew ill & Eliza ended up the property of her master's son-in-law, who sold her & her children on.
Northup obeyed Tibeats' instructions to the letter, but Tibeats somehow found fault & moved to lash Northup. Knowing he had done no wrong, Northup retaliated & totally lost it, beating Tibeats until his arm ached.
TRUE
Overseer Chapin did intervene. He was sympathetic to Northup & advised him to stay put for him own safety. He galloped off for help.
Northup stayed put. He described a well of unbearable regret welling up as he waited. Tibeats returned with two men, friends from nearby plantations.
TRUE-ISH
The 3 men bound Northup, who didn't resist, so tightly his flesh swelled up & around the rope. They put a noose around his neck & selected a tree, but Chapin intervened before they could hang him.
Although Northup wasn't hanging by his neck like in the film, he did st & in intolerable heat for hours & hours & hours. He describes excrutiating pain from the ropes & the burning ground.
TRUE
Chapin had ordered a fellow slave to gallop on Ford's fastest mule to fetch Ford back. Ford came galloping in, cut Northup's ropes.
TRUE-ISH
Northup to sleep on the floor of the 'great house' that night. Chapin, not Ford, watched over him. Northup was hired out several days later, after he'd seen Tibeats a few more times & nothing had happened. Ford instructed Tibeats sell Northup, for Northup's safety.
FALSE
Northup never told Ford of his free status, although he later regretted that he hadn't done so, since Ford was the kindest master he slaved under over his 12 years of bondage.
TRUE-ISH
Northup's new master, Tanner, addressed his new gang of slaves using bible passages, interpreted to mean disobedience should be punished with lashes. It wasn't Epps, Epps came later.
TRUE
At Epps' cotton plantation the whip was cracked from dusk 'til dawn.
Patsey was a wonder with the cotton, picking more than double a good average yield every day. Epps lusted after her.
TRUE
Slaves were expected to pick a minimum of 200lb a day. Any less & they would be whipped. Even if they surpassed that amount, they would be whipped if they then dropped below their record.
We couldn't find a source for this.
TRUE
Epps was a drunk, & frequently burst into the slave cabins at night & demanded everybody enter the house for dancing.
Any lagging or apparent lack of enthusiasm during the festivities would be punished with lashes. He bought a violin for Northup to play at these events.
TRUE
Mrs Epps was wildly jealous of Patsey & often threw broken bottles & such at her face out of the blue. Epps refused to sell her - he was infatuated, plus she was a very skilled cotton picker.
TRUE-ISH
Epps' wife did trust Northup to go & fetch things for her from the local store. In his memoir, Northup describes her as a much nicer lady than she's shown to be in the film.
We couldn't find a source for this.
TRUE
Northup often went to the store for Mrs Epps.
FALSE-ISH
Although Northup did return the groceries to Mrs Epps, there was no 'trouble' for him to lie about.
FALSE
Mrs Shaw, the slave wife of a white plantation owner, did not have Patsey & Northup over for tea. The scene was invented to 'give Mistress Shaw a voice'.
TRUE-ISH
While Patsey & Northup worked alongside each other in the fields, drunken Epps appeared gesturing for Patsey to come to him. Northup told her to ignore him. Epps picked a fight, which Mrs Epps got involved in, & Epps lied about the cause of the fight to her.
TRUE
Northup spent many nights contemplating his situation over the years.
Epps repeatedly raped & beat Patsey.
TRUE
It was during his trips to collect items for Mrs Epps that Northup decided to steal a sheet of paper from the roll she purchased.
Northup stole one sheet of paper & hid it under the boards of his hut.
TRUE-ISH
Although this particular series of events isn't described in the memoir, Northup recalls Mrs Epps having it in for Patsey, & often demanding she be lashed for no reason but her own jealousy. She did also offer goodies from her own kitchen to all but Patsey.
FALSE
This scene appears to have come from a misreading of Northup's memoir, in which he states that it was Mrs Epps who asked Northup to drown Patsey, not Patsey herself.
TRUE-ISH
Epps' fields were plagued with cotton-worm, but we don't know what he blamed it on, if anything.
Epps' hired out his cotton pickers to make money from them, since there was no cotton to pick in his fields. Northup was hired to Judge Turner.
TRUE-ISH
Although we don't know what methods Northup used to create pen & ink, he reported that he tried a number of means.
TRUE
Turner allowed Northup to play his fiddle & keep the proceeds, & he did well over the season, taking $17 on a single night once.
FALSE-ISH
Northup's violin comforted him over the years as he thought of his family, but he doesn't mention carving it with their names.
TRUE
Turner allowed Northup to play his violin at local balls & events.
We couldn't find a source for this.
Epps' wife had punished Patsey 'beyond endurance' for her husband's infatuation. There was no mention of a daughter, although Epps' regular rape of Patsey might conceivably have caused a pregnancy.
TRUE
Soon after the slaves returned to Epps' plantation they were joined by a white man, Armsby, who had hoped to be employed as an overseer & was instead put into the fields to labour alongside the slaves, a arre sight.
We couldn't find a source for this.
This scene wasn't in the memoir.
TRUE-ISH
Although we don't know whether Armbsy expressed sympathy for slaves, we do know he said enough for Northup to trust him with sending a letter on his behalf.
TRUE
Northup did offer Armsby the money he'd saved from his performances in return for him mailing a letter.
TRUE-ISH
Although probably Northup tried using sticks as pens during his trial-and-error attempts to write a letter, he ended up using a duck feather dipped in boiled maple juice.
TRUE
Armsby did tell Epps of Northup's request, & Epps challenged Northup on the matter. Northup was able to persuade him that Armsby was a liar, out to get a promotion.
Northup did burn his letter after coming so close to getting caught.
FALSE
Old Uncle Abram was still alive & working the day Northup left the plantation.
TRUE
Bass, a Canadian labourer, worked on Epps' plantation for a period alongside Northup. He was against slavery & often debated the ethics of the system with Epps & others. The conversation they had in this instance was recorded almost verbatim in the memoir.
Patsey had apparently gone missing, & nobody had seen her leave. Epps went insane, running around screaming for her in a rage.
TRUE-ISH
After a few hours Patsey returned, having visited the Shaw's from some soap as Mrs Epps refused to give her her ration. Epps didn't believe her story, despite the soap she held in her hand, & demanded Northup lash her. He didn't hold a gun to his head, though. After a while Northup stopped & refused to continue, at which point Epps took over, lashing her close to death.
TRUE
Patsey could barely move for weeks. As she lay on her stomach the other women tended to the wounds with melted tallow. Northup recalls the incident with total horror.
We couldn't find a source for this.
Not in the memoir.
TRUE
Northup, after listening to Bass' anti-slavery debates for some days, decided to take the risk of confiding in him. They talked, & Northup asked him to write to several of his friends in the North. Bass was fearful - if caught he would be killed, but agreed to post letters & more if required, to get Northup home.
A lot of time passed. They had figured a 6-week window between mailing the letters & getting a reply was reasonable, but 10 weeks & more passed with no response.
TRUE-ISH
It was Henry B. Northup, not Mr. Parker, who turned up with the sheriff that day. Epps was enraged by the whole scene, & sought legal counsel to get Northup back. Northup's people had, however, prepared substantial & extensive evidence & no lawyer would represent Epps.
TRUE
As Northup climbed into the wagon he saw Patsey & hugged her goodbye. She was happy for him but distraught that her friend & protector was leaving. She did collapse to the ground as they left.
TRUE-ISH
Northup went home to his family. Margaret had a young son named after Northup. Margaret didn't recognise her father when she opened the door to him. Alonzo was away at the time working - he had spent his life trying to raise money to buy back his father.
TRUE
Northup's kidnappers were never brought to justice. He became active in the abolitionist movement, speaking at events across the nation. Nobody knows how or where he died, or under what circumstances.
-
Original Data Provided By:
Dr Stephanie Starling, David McCandless, DM
Omid Kashan, Karl Webster
Subtitles Compiled By:
BreadCodes