Original Data Provided By:
Dr Stephanie Starling, David McCandless, DM
Omid Kashan, Karl Webster
Subtitles Compiled By:
BreadCodes
-
Unknown
We don't know for sure what state Mercury's health was in by that point, although he was diagnosed with HIV/AIDS soon afterwards.
TRUE
Princess Diana and Prince Charles were in the front row for the performance, next to Bob Geldof
Mercury adored cats and owned several as pets.
TRUE
Live Aid was unprecedented in scale. The Wembley performance drew in a 72,000-strong live audience, and another two billion watched around the world. MERCURY did have a Rolls Royce.
Professionally, Mercury was indeed fearless, despite personal insecurities. Live Aid was unprecedented in scale. The Wembley performance drew in a 72,000-strong live audience, and another two billion watched around the world.
TRUE
Mercury did work as a baggage handler at Heathrow Airport before he became a star.
Unknown
Queen were founded only two years after Conservative politician Enoch Powell’s notorious 'rivers of blood' speech and racism towards immigrants was intense. Mercury, however, had white skin and kept quiet about his roots, so he might have escaped the worst of it. We just don't know.
TRUE
Mercury was known for jotting down his lyrics and compositions on scraps of paper, something he had done since childhood.
Mercury's parents, Bomi and Jer Bulsara, were Parsis with family roots in India and Persia. Mercury was born in Zanzibar, and went to a posh boarding school in Bombay.
TRUE
Mercury was born Farrokh Bulsara, a name his mother chose because it was popular amoung the Parsis at the time. He started going by Freddie at boarding school. He changed him name legally in 1970 when Queen was formed.
As a devout man, his father didn't find Mercury's rock musician lifestyle easy to accept. Both parents hoped he would grow out of the rock star thing and return to 'proper studies'.
TRUE
Smile played loads of gigs at student bars, especially at Imperial College London where May was studying. Mercury attended many of their performances.
Tim Staffell did leave Smile to join Humpy Bong, a band that included former Bee Gees drummer Colin Petersen. The label dropped the band shortly after Staffell joined.
FALSE-ISH
Mercury didn't meet Austin the same night he met the band. Austin actually dated May first, and met Mercury once he had joined as lead singer. They remained close for the rest of Mercury's life.
TRUE
They were disappointed but they understood - Smile wasn't going anywhere.
FALSE
Mercury didn't meet the band at a gig. He had known the guys for years by the time he came to join the group.
FALSE-ISH
Mercury was mates with the band and constantly badgered the guys about becoming a member, which they relented to once Staffell had left.
TRUE
He did have four extra teeth. While he was self-conscious of his mouth, he thought the extra teeth gave his voice an edge and never got them fixed. He became famous for both his teeth and his four-octave range.
Although Mercury had a lot of personal insecurities, he was entirely confident in his professional life, never doubting his own talent.
TRUE
AUSTIN did work at Biba, which was a cool place to hang out at the time. MERCURY visited frequently over five or six months, usually with other guys from the band, before he finally asked her out.
Austin recalls that she was intrigued by the 'wild-looking artistic musician'.
TRUE-ISH
Keep Yourself Alive' was one of their earliest tracks, which they performed at various venues and student bars. But Deacon wasn't in the band at that point. He didn't join until 1971.
Unknown
Queen were founded only two years after Conservative politician Enoch Powell’s notorious 'rivers of blood' speech and racism towards immigrants was intense. Mercury, however, had white skin and kept quiet about his roots, so he might have escaped the worst of it. We just don't know.
TRUE
Mercury's mic did snap in half during an early-career show. He liked the look, and used a bottomless mic from that point onwards.
TRUE-ISH
Smile bandmate Chris Chesney recalls Mercury saying 'do your own songs and I'll make up my own words' at his audition. We don't know if he improvised lyrics during live performances, though
TRUE
It was immediately clear he was a gifted frontman.
Mercury moved into a small flat around this time, having just finished art college.
TRUE-ISH
They were totally broke in these early years. Signed with Trident production company, they barely made a penny from their success. While telling Taylor to stop breaking drumsticks because there was no money to buy more, the company manager was buying himself a Rolls Royce.
Unknown
We don't know whose idea it was to record an album.
FALSE-ISH
They all had tracks in their back pockets and took a chance opportunity to record a five-track demo at De Lane Lea studios, a precursor to their first album. It wasn't done in one night.
TRUE
The band were always looking for ways to innovate.
TRUE-ISH
EMI did get hold of a Queen demo in the early years, although not by accidentally walking into a studio.
TRUE
Mercury did design the famous Queen crest logo, utilising his talents in art and graphic design. He had a diploma from Ealing Art College.
Taylor's mum recalls Mercury explaining the new name – trying to persuade everybody it sounded 'regal'. Their friends thought it was outrageous and hilarious.
TRUE
Mercury was known for his habit of composing songs in odd positions. He did have a piano as a headboard, so that he could reach back and play what he had heard in his dreams. He had been tinkering with the 'Mama' ballad since art school, trying to figure out what to do with it.
They were very much in love, and although they didn't stay together as a couple, Mercury took care of Austin until the day he died, when he left her his property and much of his money and royalties.
TRUE-ISH
Austin's parents were both deaf. Austin did have tea with Mercury's family, although we don't know if her family were there too.
Unknown
There's no record of any naughty faux-pas happening at the family dinner.
Mercury didn't speak about his background openly in public, so it's possible he didn't bring it up with Austin and the band, but we just don't know.
FALSE-ISH
Mercury's family fled Zanzibar in 1964, to escape the revolution, but it wasn't quite a 'just the clothes on our backs' deal. His father worked for the British government. A highly privileged family, they were given six months to leave and relocated to a semi-detached house in Middlesex.
TRUE
Mercury won trophies for boxing in his youth.
Mercury did change him name legally. It wasn't just a stage name for him, but reflected who he felt he really was.
TRUE-ISH
Mercury's family were very conservative. Most of them were lawyers or accountants, and his parents thought Mercury would grow out of his rockstar dreams and settle down. It seems likely they were uncomfortable with him legally changing his name, but we're speculating.
TRUE
May did have a degree in astrophysics, and later returned to his studies to earn a PhD. Taylor did study dentistry, because his biology teacher had told him it was well paid. He eventually quit dentistry and got a degree in biology instead.
TRUE-ISH
Reid, Elton John's manager, did want to manage Queen. Apparently it was a much more complicated process than a phone call and a meeting, though.
Mercury's stage costume designer spoke of him as a free-thinker with clear ideas of what he wanted to wear. She designed his famous white cape, which had a similar batwing-inspired concertina effect to the jacket in this scene. The actual jacket Malek wore was found in Jimi Hendrix's flat after he died.
TRUE-ISH
The remaining band members have mused that Queen were never fashionable. Their fans didn't follow musical trends, and supported them through and through.
FALSE
Prenter didn't come on the scene until after Live Aid, in 1977.
TRUE-ISH
Reid did get Queen on Top of the Pops
FALSE-ISH
They did tour after their appearance on Top of the Pops, but not in Japan (that came later)
TRUE
They were certainly not happy about not actually being able to play/sing. The show was shot in the weather studio because of BBC strikes. Taylor said of the experience, 'It was rubbish, no-one actually played, just some aging disc jockeys. And the drums were plastic, so they made this "dook" noise when you hit them.'
TRUE-ISH
Queen did perform Killer Queen on TOTP, but not until later that year. Their first TOTP performance was 'Seven Seas of Rhye'. The original footage was lost several years ago.
Queen didn't tour Japan until later, during their 1974-75 Sheer Heart Attack Tour. The Japanese fans adored them, though, and their Japan sets were a bit longer than their UK and US shows.
TRUE
Mercury identified as a performer through and through, and felt Austin was the only true friend he ever had.
TRUE-ISH
Austin remembers, 'He gave me a big box on Christmas Day. Inside was another box, then another and so it went on... Eventually, I found a lovely jade ring inside the last small box.' Like in the movie, she asked which finger she should put it on, and he asked her to marry him, and she whispered her yes.
FALSE
We don't know if this happened or not, but Austin doesn't mention this when she talks about the proposal in an interview
TRUE
Queen toured the US for the first time in 1974 after their record Queen I hit the charts
The tour was a massive hit.
FALSE-ISH
There was no Ray Foster. There's a rumour that the character is loosely based on Roy Featherstone (the band's A&R guy at EMI) but represented a whole bunch of EMI execs.
TRUE
The band nicknamed Jim Beach 'Miami', a play on his last name.
Queen didn't like to repeat the same formula, and were always looking for ways to innovate. Mercury wanted the new record to be operatic, and the band were all for it.
TRUE-ISH
Queen did record 'Bohemian Rhapsody' at Rockfield Studios, a farmhouse-turned-recording-studio opened by two farmers, Kingsley and Charles Ward.
TRUE
Mercury was known for jotting down his lyrics and compositions on scraps of paper, something he had done since childhood.
FALSE
Prenter wasn't at Rockfield Farm - he wasn't hired until 1977.
TRUE-ISH
Mercury wrote the song for Austin, of whom he later said, 'the only friend I've got is Mary, and I don't want anybody else'.
FALSE-ISH
Prenter and Mercury did end up as lovers, but he didn't come on the scene for another two years.
TRUE
May thought the song was a joke when he first heard it. Taylor insisted it became the B-side to 'Bohemian Rhapsody' and locked himself in a cupboard until Mercury agreed. Writers of the A- and B-sides had to split the record royalties equally, so Taylor raked in the rewards from Mercury's 'Bohemian Rhapsody' success.
Mercury did finalise his composition at Rockfield Farm.
TRUE
May wrote that famous guitar solo, which Mercury thought was wonderful.
Mercury would flounce in during the sessions saying 'I've just added a few more Galileos, dear'. The 24-track tape was passed through the machines so many times it was almost transparent by the time the recording was complete. The band revelled in the creativity. Mercury wanted to 'go well over the top'.
TRUE-ISH
Several EMI execs were concerned that the track was too long for radio. One exec, Paul Watts, recalled 'when they played me Bohemian Rhapsody my reaction was, "what the fuck's this? Are you mad?"'.
FALSE-ISH
There's no record of Queen storming out, but there was some tension over all this.
TRUE-ISH
Mercury did throw a brick through a window, but not at EMI. After a row with Reid, Mercury launched a brick through the window of Reid's Knightsbridge home, and stood on the street yelling until Reid invited him in.
TRUE
Everett was pivotal in getting the track out there. Some say he was sent a demo and told not to play it, others say he stole it. He played it 14 times in one weekend, claiming on every play that 'his finger slipped'. Mercury did make an appearance on Everett's breakfast show, but not that particular broadcast.
TRUE-ISH
Mercury met Everett when he appeared on his breakfast show. They didn't hook up but they did hit it off, and the pair were a staple on the London club scene.
TRUE
Bohemian Rhapsody' bombed with the critics, drawing all the comments shown in the film.
Crowds went wild for Queen's 'Bohemian Rhapsody' performance at Edinburgh in 1976. The show won them a standing ovation.
TRUE
Queen's 'A Night at the Opera' tour took in a whopping 77 performances
Austin knew that something was wrong between them during the final two years of their six-year relationship. Freddie would indeed call to speak to his cats while he was away on tour.
TRUE
Austin has said she knew he was with men during the last years of their relationship.
TRUE-ISH
Mercury and Prenter did end up lovers, but not until a couple of years later. During their time together there hookups and hotel rooms galore.
TRUE
And she was. Mercury said of her, 'to me, she was my common-law wife. To me, it was a marriage', replacing her was 'simply impossible'. Austin was a big part of his will after he passed away. She received his property, much of his money and his royalties.
Austin figured out that Mercury was into men long before he told her, and she was right. Austin remembers saying ‘No Freddie, I don’t think you are bisexual. I think you are gay.' Mercury always refused to define his sexuality publically, so it's unclear whether he was gay, bisexual or otherwise.
TRUE
They did end their engagement after Mercury came out. He told her he wanted her to always be part of his life.
Mercury bought a mansion in Kensington, known as Garden Lodge. Mercury did treat his cats like his children.
TRUE
Mercury never stopped adoring Austin and always wanted her around. The record company bought her a place near Mercury when she moved out of their shared home.
TRUE-ISH
Mercury threw extraordinary parties. There were trolls, dwarfs, ogres, thieves, ballerinas, transvestites, flamenco dancers, fireworks... His grand parties went on for days, weeks. For one party, guests had to dress as their favourite person. MERCURY dressed as himself. Prenter wasn't on the scene yet, though.
TRUE
Mercury was known for these grand parties, and for his lavish gifts.
TRUE-ISH
Austin watched from the sidelines to some extent during Mercury's years with Prenter. Taylor couldn't stand the guy. All this came later, though. Prenter wasn't on the scene yet.
Mercury and May fell out all the time
TRUE
Prenter is often accused of leading Mercury astray, encouraging a wild lifestyle. They partied constantly.
FALSE
This never happened. Mercury met Hutton at Heaven, one of London's premier gay nightclubs.
FALSE-ISH
Hutton did reject Mercury the first time they met, but it was a 'fuck off' in a bar, not an insightful distancing.
TRUE
MAY came up with the idea for a song that audience could get involved with after being inspired by the audience singing 'You'll Never Walk Alone' to Queen at the end of a gig. He went to sleep thinking, they can stamp their feet, clap their hands, and sing. And he woke up with 'We Will Rock You' in his head.
TRUE-ISH
Mercury and May fell out all the time, especially during the Prenter years.
TRUE
Like May, Mercury was into the idea of a track that really involved the audience. He was all for 'We Will Rock You', and wrote 'We Are the Champions' to release alongside it.
May has described the Madison Square Garden gig as a landmark moment for the band, a magical experience.
TRUE
Mercury is considered one of the greatest frontmen of all time, always able to command audiences. They lapped up his call and response bit.
TRUE-ISH
Mercury was interested in going solo, but Prenter and Reid weren't involved in Queen's management at this stage.
TRUE
CBS did offer Mercury massive money for a solo album.
FALSE
Reid and Prenter weren't in the picture at this stage.
Unknown
We don't know what Mercury felt about Austin's lovers.
FALSE
Reid and Prenter weren't in the picture at this stage.
Mercury actually wanted to go solo and Reid was no longer involved with the band at this point. Reid later said he'd never had any problems with Queen, and 'that's been one of the gentlest parting of the ways of anybody I've ever worked with'. Taylor has said the band had a 'good working relationship with John'.
FALSE
Prenter didn't come into Mercury's life until years after Reid had ceased managing Queen.
TRUE-ISH
The exposé was published, although not until later. Prenter sold his story, along with photos of Mercury with various lovers, to The Sun newspaper for £32,000. They ran with the header 'All the Queen's Men'.
Later than shown in the film – in the late 70s – Prenter tried to steer the bands sound towards disco and funk. His influence on their style created tension. Taylor and May were especially resentful and the band often fought when the pressure was on.
FALSE-ISH
They did part ways with Reid, but the band were all agreed on it
TRUE
Beach became their manager after the band left Reid's management
TRUE-ISH
Later than shown in the film – in the late 70s – Prenter tried to steer the bands sound towards disco and funk. His influence on their style created tension. Taylor and May were especially resentful.
TRUE
The band argued constantly, especially when the pressure was on. Mercury and Taylor were the hotheads of the group.
TRUE-ISH
May was always the most sensitive in the band, wanting everybody to be happy, but he could be ruthless when he wanted to be and admits he rarely backed down.
TRUE
Deacon was very down to earth and calm and he remained that way. Always much more a family man than a rockstar, it took him years to even start finding his voice with the other guys, and he virtually became a recluse in later life.
TRUE-ISH
Deacon did write 'Another One Bites the Dust', which Michael Jackson suggested be released as a single. It was a massive number one hit and won an American Music Award. However, it wasn't released until much later – 1980.
TRUE
Beach became their manager after the band left Reid's management
TRUE-ISH
Mercury took to the gay scene like a duck to water. He didn't meet Prenter until later on, but they were immersed in it, especially while working in Munich.
Once Mercury started getting sick he struggled terribly in the studio, but this didn't come until later.
TRUE-ISH
The press absolutely hounded Mercury, vilifying him for his sexuality and his wild lifestyle. The press conference in the scene was a conglomeration of the worst of it, quoting parts from various interviews over the years. Mercury and the band found it unbearable.
TRUE
Mercury admitted he suffered loneliness: 'Because audiences love me, it’s hard for them to believe that somebody like Freddie Mercury could be lonely’ ‘In fact, my kind of loneliness is the hardest. I can be in a crowd and still be the loneliest person, because I don’t really belong to anyone’.
The video for 'I Want to Break Free' featured the entire band in drag, a parody of Coronation Street.
FALSE
Mercury met Hutton in a nightclub, he didn't use the phonebook to search London for him.
TRUE
MTV banned the 'I Want to Break Free' video. Deacon wrote the song and Taylor came up with the drag idea. The theme was a parody of Coronation Street, but the humour was lost on US audiences. Mercury did pull away from Queen at this time, recording his first solo track the same year 'I Want to Break Free' was released.
FALSE-ISH
The band fought a lot and it often got personal. They did take a break at this point, but it was unanimous. Mercury wanted to pursue solo projects, but so did the others. May has said, 'It was breaking up the whole time! All of us left the band at some point, and not just one time - all the way through.'
Unknown
Prenter was accused of preventing Mercury from appearing on radio shows and having excessive control over his life. We don't know if he tried to keep Austin away, though.
TRUE
Other band members have said that Queen's arguments, the battle of egos, pushed every track to it's max potential. Without that, Mercury's output lost its edge, and he quickly returned to working with Queen instead.
TRUE-ISH
May describes this period of sex, drugs, and partying with Prenter as a dangerous and vulnerable time for Mercury. This didn't happen until later, though.
Mercury likely experienced this symptom as a result of the AIDS-related respiratory disease that ultimately caused his death. However, signs of his illness didn't come until a year or two later.
TRUE-ISH
We don't know if Austin visited Mercury in Munich. But there's no doubt he was consuming a lot of alcohol and a lot of cocaine at this point in his life (which came later than the film's timeline). She has said all she could do was watch from the sidelines.
FALSE
Mercury did know what Live Aid was, and wasn't keen to take part.
Unknown
Mercury always wanted Austin close, and she did have children during those years. But we don't know if this conversation ever happened.
We don't know if this ever happened.
Unknown
Those close to Mercury were worried about his life in Munich with Prenter. They saw him as vulnerable and living a dangerous lifestyle. Mercury had started to see it himself, too. We don't know if Austin went to Munich to try and bring him home, though.
TRUE-ISH
Their relationship broke down after Mercury ditched the drinking, drugs and parties. Queen's former roadie recalls that the final straw was when Prenter threw a party at Mercury's house and trashed the place. Mercury fired him, and like in the film, Prenter did rant and rave and threaten to expose him.
FALSE
Prenter sold his story to the papers, he didn't appear on TV.
TRUE
Prenter sold his story to the Sun newspaper for £32,000. He provided photos of Mercury with various lovers and told the world about his lifestyle, and how much he feared AIDS.
FALSE
Mercury was actually reticent about Live Aid, and the band weren't that disconnected after Mercury did his solo thing. Taylor recalls, 'I don't think Freddie really wanted to go solo... when it came down to actually doing a solo album, he did sort of miss us'. Both May and Taylor appeared on Mercury's first solo single.
FALSE-ISH
Prenter did talk publically about Mercury being afraid to be alone, but there's no record of him using racist slurs against him.
FALSE
Queen had numerous meetings about their status as a group, whether they were breaking up or not. They didn't ever actually break up, though.
TRUE-ISH
Mercury did tell Beach about his diagnosis before he told the rest of the band, but it was later on.
The band members didn't share songwriting credits for an entire album until 1989's 'The Miracle'.
TRUE-ISH
May and Taylor have both said that Prenter was 'a very, very bad influence upon Freddie', and on the band. They didn't want him around. Mercury did fire Prenter eventually, but it wasn't until 1986.
TRUE
The line-up had been published and every ticket sold before Queen agreed to join in last-minute. The biggest names in music were all performing.
FALSE
The band were actually very much together and very-well rehearsed by time Live Aid came around. They had released 'The Works' in 1984 and had been touring, with the last tour date just eight weeks before Live Aid. Mercury was actually reticent to do Live Aid, but was persuaded by Geldof.
TRUE
The FDA approved the first ever blood test to screen for HIV in 1985.
Mercury lived in fear of contracting HIV, particularly after his friends and lovers started to die from AIDS.
TRUE-ISH
Mercury did have an AIDS test in 1985, although the results were negative. He was tested again in 1987, when he recieved his positive diagnosis – later than shown in the film.
Unknown
Nobody knows what happened at those appointments.
TRUE-ISH
In the film there's the suggestion that this cough was part of Mercury's declining health due to AIDS. In reality, he did have a sore throat during Live Aid rehearsals, and performed against his doctor's advice. But it was just a throat infection.
TRUE
BEACH did know about Mercury's diagnosis before the band did. Mercury told him, but asked him to keep it secret.
FALSE
Mercury didn't confirm his diagnosis to his bandmates until 1989, not 1985 as shown in the film. Although they had worked it out for themselves much earlier.
TRUE
When Mercury told the band he had AIDS, he insisted that he didn't want it discussed further, he just wanted to ignore it and make music until 'I fucking well drop'. That was the only direct conversation they ever had about it. The band were all devastated.
TRUE-ISH
There's some great footage of Mercury doing vocal warmups, although not from Live Aid day.
TRUE
Geldof was broadcast live several times throughout the concert, pushing for donations. He did swear during one of them, which was all very exciting for the folks at the BBC
FALSE
In the film, this is the second time they met. In reality, the second time they met was at Heaven nightclub in London – the same spot as their first meeting. The first time, Hutton turned down a drink from Mercury. A year and a half later, just before Live Aid, he accepted the same offer.
Unknown
We don't know if Mercury ever introduced Hutton to his parents. He never came out to them, though.
We don't know how Austin felt about Hutton, although there are rumours of hostility between them in later years. However, Austin has said she was relieved and euphoric to finally see Mercury living his sexuality freely.
Unknown
We don't know what Mercury thought of Austin's lovers.
TRUE-ISH
The PA limiters were switched so that Queen's performance would be louder, but this was done by Queen's sound engineer, not Beach.
TRUE
Mercury owned the stage the moment he stepped out, making 'the world his stadium'
Almost seven hours in, Live Aid had raised just £1.2 million, and Geldof was sorely disappointed.
TRUE
Mecury did open Queen's section sitting at the piano, playing Bohemian Rhapsody. He even adjusted a knob like in the movie. The audience sang along, 'as if this was what they had waited for all day'.
TRUE-ISH
Mercury was very close to his mum. She always came to see Queen when they played nearby. She always supported his musical endeavors. Mercury can be seen blowing a kiss to the camera as he sings the 'Mama' ballad at Live Aid, although we don't know if it was to his mother.
Hutton did watch the Live Aid performance from backstage. We don't know if Austin and her boyfriend were with him.
TRUE
The crowds went wild for 'Radio Ga Ga', slapping their hands overhead and pumping their fists.
Mercury launched into his famous 'ay-oh!' call and response, determined to reach every person watching.
TRUE-ISH
Geldof, pumped up by Queen's amazing performance, gave a shouty interview full of profanities, calling for donations. After his outburst, donations increased to £300 per second.
TRUE
Mercury's stage-craft and energy that night became legendary, with many calling it one of the best live performances in history. May has said it was the greatest day of their lives. Elton John told them, 'You bastards, you stole the show!'
He died at his Kensington home in Nov 24th, 1991, having made a public statement revealing his battle with AIDS the day before.
TRUE
Mercury and Hutton were together for almost seven years, and lived together at Mercury's home. He and Austin were close until his last day, and he left his mansion to her.
Mercury had a traditional Zoroastrian cremation.
TRUE
In its five-week stand, it sold almost a million copies. It was the only single to become Christmas Number One on two separate occasions, and was voted the nation's favourite number one single of the past 60 years in 2012.
The Mercury Phoenix Trust has so far provided $17 million to projects in 56 countries.
-
Original Data Provided By:
Dr Stephanie Starling, David McCandless, DM
Omid Kashan, Karl Webster
Subtitles Compiled By:
BreadCodes