Original Data Provided By:
Dr Stephanie Starling, David McCandless, DM
Omid Kashan, Karl Webster
Subtitles Compiled By:
BreadCodes
-
TRUE
Phillips was always well prepared for his trips.
Andrea & Phillips live together in Vermont. She's a nurse.
TRUE
Phillips was very much a family man. When not at sea, he was with his children full-time. Andrea always drove him to the airport when he had to fly out.
Andrea dropped Phillips off & drove away, just as in the film. Traditionally she would wait with the kids until the plane took off, but there wasn't time that day.
We don't have the pirates' side of things.
We don't have the pirates' side of the story. 3 of the 4 were shot dead by Navy SEALS, & the remaining pirate, now in jail, refused to speak to the filmmakers.
TRUE
Phillips was taken to the port at Salalah by car.
When Phillips boarded the Maersk Alabama in port he checked it over for several hours, & found security measures had slipped. Doors were unlocked, pirate cages not shut, etc.
TRUE
Phillips already knew Shane & Mike, & worked well with them. All three were serious & proactive. The rest he got along with ok at first meeting, although he was unsure about one of the senior sailors. Phillips was known for being tough with his crew.
The Maersk Alabama was carrying commercial cargo, along with freshwater & food aid for Kenya.
TRUE
The route through from Salalah to Mombasa was known as the EAF4 run (East Africa 4).
Phillips was hot on security & ordered the crew to take extra care.
TRUE
The Maersk Alabama set sail from Salalah in April 2009.
Phillips was safety conscious & walked the boat up & down doing checks before they set sail.
FALSE-ISH
This incident wasn't recorded in the memoir, although Phillips was known for being a hard taskmaster, & many of the crew disliked him.
We don't have the pirates' side of things.
We don't have the pirates' side of the story. 3 of the 4 were shot dead by Navy SEALS, & the remaining pirate, now in jail, refused to speak to the filmmakers.
TRUE
Phillips received a number of bulletins about pirate activity off the Somali coast. Since 2005 sailing the Horn of Africa had become extremely dangerous, with hijacks, shootings, etc. One bulletin reported 39 attacks in a single week.
Phillips ordered a pirate intrusion drill. Shane is keen, the third mate, Colin Wright, was hesitant but followed orders.
TRUE
The crew tested the pirate hoses as part of the drill. A valve had been left open & there was no water.
Phillips noticed three blips on the screen.
TRUE
Phillips used the binoculars to identify what he thought might be a pirate mothership & a couple of 'skiffs', small wooden boats with little engines.
FALSE
Phillips was portrayed as more of a team player in the film than he was in reality. He left his crew to carry on with the fire drill they had been conducting while he decided what to do about the pirates.
TRUE
Phillips upped the speed, the chief engineer let him know how far they could push the engine.
Maritime Emergency didn't pick up. UKMTO were condescending & unhelpful, but took details.
We don't have the pirates' side of things.
We don't have the pirates' side of the story. 3 of the 4 were shot dead by Navy SEALS, & the remaining pirate, now in jail, refused to speak to the filmmakers.
TRUE-ISH
Phillips kept the chief engineer in the loop regarding speed, notifying him of any increases. The engineer let him know that the ship engines were ok. However, the captain didn't have to request clearance as such.
TRUE
The small boats were struggling against the waves.
Phillips pretended to be in contact with the navy, faked a radio call, attempting to trick the pirates into thinking they were armed & air support was coming.
TRUE
One of the small boats did turn around at that point.
FALSE-ISH
Phillips kept the chief engineer in the loop regarding speed, notifying him of any increases. The engineer let him know that the ship engines were ok. However, the captain didn't have to request clearance as such.
TRUE
The pirates got pretty close, around 4 miles away.
Phillips put the ship into manoeuvres, which created waves & tossed the little pirate boats around.
The little boats struggled in the water.
Although we don't have the pirates' side of the story, the little boat was clearly struggling on the waves & couldn't keep up in the swell of the ship. They had put the little boats into the water off the mothership at too great a distance.
TRUE-ISH
Phillips addressed the crew after the first attack, debriefing them & giving tips in case it happened again. The book doesn't record him praising them, though.
Members of the crew did approach Phillips with their fears after the first incident, although the memoir doesn't record any conversations about pay or rights.
FALSE-ISH
Phillips did email his wife regularly, but he always told her the truth about the bad stuff.
We don't have the pirates' side of things.
We don't have the pirates' side of the story. 3 of the 4 were shot dead by Navy SEALS, & the remaining pirate, now in jail, refused to speak to the filmmakers.
TRUE-ISH
There were 3 pirate incidents in the book, whereas the film records only 2, rolling the second 2 into 1. In the 2nd incident, Ken radioed Phillips to come to the bridge - pirates were calling over the radio.
At the third pirate encounter Phillips was already on the bridge, he ordered a change of course & increased speed. He reported to UKMTO, rather than US Maritime Emergency.
TRUE-ISH
This part was a blend of the second & third incidents. In the second incident, the pirates radioed the ship. In the third incident, they opened fire.
The crew turned the protective hoses on, but no mention of one being broken. However, they did fail against the pirates & they were able to get on board with ease.
TRUE-ISH
Phillips didn't order the crew to the engine room, but they knew that was their safe room. Phillips let the bosun know what was happening so he could round up the men, while Phillips stayed on the bridge.
TRUE
The pirates did shoot into the bridge. Phillips put in a sly call to the engine room to close of the steering from the bridge & take over the controls from down there.
FALSE-ISH
This didn't happen, but Phillips hoped they would stay hidden & refused to tell the pirates where they were.
TRUE-ISH
They had agreed on a safe room & a back up safe room earlier in the trip. One was through the engine room & in after steering.
TRUE
They got into the bridge within 5 minutes of boarding the ship. They were armed with AK47s.
TRUE-ISH
The pirate leader did implore them to relax & give in, it was 'just business'. At a later stage Phillips offered them the $30k that was in the safe.
TRUE
Because the engineers had closed off control from the bridge, it appeared to the pirates that the ship was broken, much to their frustration.
The whole ship was burning up without the AC & ventilation systems running.
TRUE
Phillips told the pirates they had broken the ship by slowing it down too fast, & it was now circling in the water. The pirates got annoyed & demanded they stop the ship immediately, turn it completely off.
The pirate leader demanded the crew come to the bridge. Phillips put out several calls on the radio but his crew didn't respond. He had told them previously to hide in a safe room. The pirates threatened to kill Colin & ATM if the crew didn't arrive within the minute.
FALSE
Phillips never asked that the pirates shoot him to protect his crew.
TRUE-ISH
The leader did demand to search the ship after one crew member wandered onto the bridge. Phillips wasn't exactly sure where his crew were & if they all knew the situation. He didn't radio a warning, but did stall as much as possible.
FALSE
There was nothing written about disabling the lights in the memoir.
TRUE-ISH
The pirates did demand to search the ship, although no map was mentioned in the book, & it wasn't Phillips who led them round.
Although it wasn't the galley, Shane was moving around the ship during the attack.
TRUE-ISH
Shane was hiding in more than one of the rooms the pirates entered. Phillips didn't know until afterwards that he had been there at all. Although it happened slightly later than this point in the movie, Phillips did give melons & juice boxes to the pirates.
FALSE
The broken glass thing didn't happen.
TRUE
Two crew members, Colin & ATM, were on the bridge with Phillips when the pirates attacked.
FALSE
The broken glass thing didn't happen.
TRUE-ISH
Chief Engineer Mike Perry played a huge role in the event, ambushing & capturing the pirate leader single-handedly. This throwing incident wasn't recorded, though.
Muse did go searching for the crew, although he didn't enter the safe room, which was through the engine room & into aft steering.
FALSE-ISH
Although this incident wasn't recorded in the book, we do know that Mike used his knowledge of the ship to capture the pirate leader.
TRUE
As Phillips led Muse around the engine room, Muse grew nervous of the dark & demanded to leave.
FALSE-ISH
Mike certainly had one-to-one dealings with the pirates, but it was Mike who went after the pirate, not vice-versa.
FALSE
The broken glass thing didn't happen.
TRUE
The pirates were on the bridge, angry that the boat wasn't working.
TRUE-ISH
Mike alone attacked the pirate leader with a knife, cutting his hand badly.
FALSE
The broken glass thing didn't happen.
TRUE
Mike the chief engineer captured the leader & used him to make a deal.
TRUE-ISH
Phillips made this deal with the pirates while the crew had their leader hostage. The pirates were to leave, with the cash, & be given their leader back, in return for Phillips' release.
TRUE
Phillips did show them the lifeboat, & they awaited the return of their captured leader.
TRUE-ISH
Phillips had to get into the lifeboat with the pirates to release it, show them how it worked, etc. It was his idea for them to take the lifeboat, they had initially tried another smaller on-board vessel, but the battery had been dead.
TRUE
The crew released the pirate leader they had caught & he boarded the lifeboat.
TRUE-ISH
Nobody physcially knocked Phillips into the lifeboat - he was already inside. But they did refuse to release him, as had been the deal.
TRUE
The USS Bainbridge assisted the Maersk Alabama, & stayed with Phillips until they were able to rescue him.
TRUE-ISH
The lifeboat was hot & cramped. The boy hadn't cut his foot, but there was plenty of complaining on other counts. The leader had been injured when the crew captured him.
FALSE
There is no mention of the pirates discussing things like this with Phillips.
TRUE-ISH
The Alabama fired up & started following the lifeboat. When the pirates noticed it was working fine afterall, they were annoyed. They joked about reboarding in the morning to take the ship.
TRUE
The Alabama followed the lifeboat until they were ordered to clear out by the US Navy.
FALSE-ISH
Phillips recalled that after a few days in the lifeboat the pirates fought each other constantly. Phillips did mention khat in his memoir, but only in passing reference. It has to be smoked immediately after harvesting, so no good on an extended journey.
TRUE-ISH
Although Muse didn't talk to Phillips about this, pirates of the region did claim that foreign trawlers had stolen their fish & dumped hazardous waste in their ocean, undermining their trade as fishermen & leading them to desperate measures.
The leader had a gashed hand, which he allowed Phillips to clean with the first aid kit.
TRUE-ISH
Phillips had this knife with him all along. When he opened it to cut the bandage the pirates were surprised, & took it. Not the big event it was made out to be in the film, though.
TRUE
The military were on the case, equipped with a ScanEagle drone.
Garaad is known as the 'Pirate King of Somalia'. He claims to be on a mission to stop what he deems illegal international fishing in Somalian waters. His gangs hijack various types of boats, including trawlers, tugs & yachts.
TRUE
There was plenty of drinking water on the lifeboat, but the pirates rationed Phillips' supply.
FALSE
This incident didn't feature in the book.
TRUE-ISH
Hufan doesn't feature in the book, although we know there was a mothership, & the whole operation was overseen by Garaad, who had a whole hierarchy of men working for him. A Hufan-type character presumably existed.
FALSE
Garaad is notoriously tough on his men, & expects millions out of the hijackings he funds.
TRUE
The SEAL team worked with the other Navy crews to negotiate for Phillips' release. The White House was aware of the situation, & Obama authorised the use of lethal force in dealing with it.
One pirate tried to smash the plexiglass window with a loaded AK47. Phillips warned the leader what could happen & the leader made the guy take the clip out.
TRUE
The leader boasted about his previous successes, including a $6m payout. Phillips responded just like in the film.
Phillips frequently had a gun to his head while on the lifeboat, & the pirates fought each other constantly.
TRUE
A navy ship arrived in the night, the lights & sirens startling the pirates. It was the USS Bainbridge.
Castellano, although not trained in negotiation, was charged with dealing with the pirates.
TRUE
The Navy had a Somali interpreter. He arranged for food & water to be sent to the lifeboat.
The Alabama crew wanted to stay with their captain, but the Navy boarded the ship & ordered them to continue on their journey to Mombasa.
TRUE
The Navy did send out a boat with supplies.
We don't have the pirates' side of things.
We don't have the pirates' side of the story. 3 of the 4 were shot dead by Navy SEALS, & the remaining pirate, now in jail, refused to speak to the filmmakers.
TRUE
The Navy did send out a boat with supplies.
The Navy ships were equipped with hi tech gadgets.
TRUE-ISH
Phillips did let his crew know which seat he was in to protect himself from friendly fire. However, he did this via his radio, which, for some reason, the pirates let him keep throughout.
TRUE
At one point the pirates fired shots next to Phillips' head to torment him. They wanted more than the $30,000 they took, & planned to get millions from the insurance company.
Although the pirates initially seemed quite jovial, they soon turned to in-fighting when things got tense.
TRUE
The Navy was in regular contact with the lifeboat.
FALSE
This wasn't recorded in the book. It seemed Muse was fairly willing to talk to the Navy - he wanted to go aboard the ship to get injuries seen to.
TRUE
A further two military vessels arrived as backup, the USS Boxer & the USS Arleigh Burke.
FALSE
The on-screen relationship between Phillips & Muse wasn't a feature of the book, it doesn't seem that they had these kinds of conversations.
TRUE
Castellano was the commander of the USS Bainbridge during the hijacking.
The pirates hoped to get Phillips to Somalia where they could hide him somewhere & hold him for ransom.
TRUE
The SEALS did indeed parachute into the Indian Ocean, under the cover of night.
TRUE-ISH
Three of the four pirates were asleep at one point, & the fourth went out to urinate. Phillips had been allowed to do the same earlier, but on this occasion, he snuck out.
TRUE
Phillips did push the urinating pirate into the ocean, & jumped in behind him.
Phillips found out after the incident that by the time the Navy had ascertained that it was him in the water, it was too late.
TRUE
Phillips tried to swim the half mile to the USS Bainbridge. The pirates were going wild, guns out, searching for him.
Phillips found out afterwards that while the Navy had been watching the whole thing, they couldn't be sure it was him in the water until it was too late.
TRUE
The pirates recaptured Phillips.
The SEALS were brought in to assist.
TRUE-ISH
The pirates dragged Phillips back onto the lifeboat. They all beat him, not just one.
TRUE
As the pressure on the pirates increased, they argued more & more. The Navy hoped for a peaceful solution but were authorised to use lethal force. Helicopters were used.
TRUE-ISH
This exact incident wasn't recorded in the book, but Phillips frequently had a gun to his head, & the Navy were watching & planning throughout Phillips' capture.
TRUE
The Navy were following every move.
FALSE-ISH
Phillips recalled the pirates on the radio to the Navy, joking around, requesting a body bag. Around the same stage, the pirates tried to get Phillips to stand on the orange survival suit - something to do with their halal ritual.
TRUE-ISH
Phillips didn't write about these meaningful moments with the leader, rather, the leader seemed more distant than he was depicted in the film. Still, the pirates did point a gun at Phillips' head & there was a lot of radio contact.
FALSE-ISH
The leader did go onboard to negotiate. The pirates agreed to a tow because they'd drifted off course & were expecting a violent reception from a rival tribe if they landed in the wrong spot. No mention of any ruse using tribal elders.
TRUE
The Navy towed the lifeboat in. The pirate leader went aboard the navy ship.
FALSE
The on-screen relationship between Phillips & Muse wasn't a feature of the book, it doesn't seem that they had these kinds of conversations.
TRUE
The Navy did persuade the pirates to let them tow the boat, ostensibly to keep it safe in rough waters.
They gave him a bright yellow tshirt & blue trousers so they could identify him easily.
TRUE
The leader did board the Navy boat.
FALSE
The pirates actually insisted Phillips wear the uniform. The Navy didn't send instructions to Phillips, but did write a message of support on a sauce bottle they provided with other supplies.
TRUE
The Navy claim that they brought the leader on board to discuss a deal, but Phillips didn't believe them, thought the leader had sensed bad things coming & ditched his pals.
Phillips was guarded by armed pirates throughout his capture.
TRUE
The USS Bainbridge had great bright floodlights, which they agreed to turn off overnight so that everybody could rest. The Navy did tow the lifeboat.
The Navy team reported that they had plenty of occasions where they could have taken the pirates out, but were too concerned for Phillips' safety to risk shooting.
FALSE
The pirates gave the uniform to Phillips straight off.
TRUE
The Navy crew, due to some other mission they were involved in, had all kinds of hi-tech spy-type equipment on board, & put it to use.
The Navy engaged in 'aggressive' manoeuvering to throw the lifeboat.
FALSE-ISH
Indeed the pirates didn't like the chop the Navy was creating. Phillips didn't grab a biro, though.
FALSE
As the winds picked up the pirates got stressed by the choppy waves. The Navy persuaded them to allow the lifeboat to be towed for a smoother ride, hoping to calm them down.
Phillips was tied up & couldn't have written a note. Although there was a young pirate in the group, he didn't have the kind streak that he is shown to have in the film.
TRUE
The Bainbridge stayed with the lifeboat, trying to figure out a way to rescue Phillips without risking his life.
FALSE
Phillips was tied up & couldn't have written a note. Although there was a young pirate in the group, he didn't have the kind streak that he is shown to have in the film.
FALSE-ISH
Phillips couldn't have written a note, but he did conjur up images of his family, & spoke as if his wife were there with him. At this point Phillips was already tied up, the pirates planned to kill him & had been making arrangements for a halal killing.
TRUE
They brought the lifeboat in closer & closer using the towline, so that they could get a better angle for a shot. They didn't have proper sniper rifles on board, so range needed to be short.
Phillips maintained composure for several days, but by this point, had had enough & had given up on his life.
TRUE
Snipers were watching & waiting for the right time to shoot.
The pirates tied & blindfolded Phillips in a particular way, adhering to some kind of religious ritual that required chanting & red & white fabric. These details were left out of the film. Phillips reports that he felt regret for his family at that moment.
TRUE
Snipers were watching & waiting for the right time to shoot.
One of the pirates went to shoot Phillips, another screamed not to do it. They argued.
TRUE
While the Navy were trying to solve the situation, the pirates had stopped treating Phillips like a human & had started making him do strange, degrading things. He did eventually snap, screamed he'd had enough, felt he was ready to die.
The snipers waited a long time shoot, concerned they could hit Phillips by mistake.
TRUE
Navy SEALS thought the pirates were going to shoot Phillips so they fired.
Navy SEALS had killed every one of the pirates on the lifeboat, showering Phillips with blood.
TRUE
A Navy guy tried to get into the lifeboat but the pirates had tied the hatch shut from the inside. Phillips loosened the knots & the Navy guy entered & checked him over.
Muse was brought onto the boat to treat his injuries & discuss a deal. Once on-board, he was held captive.
TRUE
Phillips was brought aboard the Navy ship. Three pirates were shot, one captured.
TRUE-ISH
Phillips didn't really go into the emotional side of his rescue so we don't know how he felt, although he did admit to waking up in tears for several days afterwards, & to reluctantly speaking to a SEAL psychiatrist.
TRUE
Muse was tried in the USA.
Phillips was attended to by a medic, his injuries were not severe but he was traumatised.
-
TRUE
Muse was put on trial in the USA. His family tried to claim he should be tried as a juvenile, but he eventually admitted he was 18 & was sentenced as an adult. He was given 33 years & 9 months in a federal prison.
-
Original Data Provided By:
Dr Stephanie Starling, David McCandless, DM
Omid Kashan, Karl Webster
Subtitles Compiled By:
BreadCodes