Original Data Provided By:
Dr Stephanie Starling, David McCandless, DM
Omid Kashan, Karl Webster
Subtitles Compiled By:
BreadCodes
-
Martin was barely featured in the book.
The film creates a story out of the relationship between Martin & Philomena. In the book, Martin is barely there. We don't hear about his life, his feelings, or his relationships with those involved.
TRUE
Martin was the Director of Communications for the Department of Transport. A scandal known as 'Spingate' had him wrongly ousted from his position, after a row with Stephen Buyers & Alistair Campbell. Martin received compensation.
Martin was barely featured in the book.
The film creates a story out of the relationship between Martin & Philomena. In the book, Martin is barely there. We don't hear about his life, his feelings, or his relationships with those involved.
TRUE
Tony Blair backed Transport Secretary Stephen Byers over his row with Martin.
Martin was barely featured in the book.
The film creates a story out of the relationship between Martin & Philomena. In the book, Martin is barely there. We don't hear about his life, his feelings, or his relationships with those involved.
TRUE
Philomena remained a devout Catholic all her life.
Philomena Lee met John McInerney at the Limerick Carnival.
Not in the book.
This incident wasn't recorded in the book, & we don't know if the real Philomena ever had a hip replacement.
TRUE
It was at a fairground where Philomena became pregnant.
The mother superior at the convent blamed all of the girls for their 'sins of the flesh', regardless of how they became pregnant. They were made to tell the details of their 'sin'. Philomena hadn't been taught about sex at the convent where she grew up, & her mother had died before she could teach her.
TRUE
Sister Annunciata was charged with delivering the baby, while the other nuns prayed. The baby was breach, but no painkillers were allowed for sinners. Philomena tore but was not allowed to be stitched up.
TRUE-ISH
Philomena admitted she had a lost son to her family in 2003, when he would have been 51. Jane was aware of the photograph, but she had been told the boy was a distant cousin. She retrieved it from the drawer, knowing immediately who it was.
TRUE
She gave birth to a boy at a Roscrea in Country Tipperary on July 5th 1952.
Martin was at a New Year's Eve party.
TRUE-ISH
Martin was approached by a friend of Philomena's daughter at a party, although she wasn't waitressing. She told him she had a puzzle for him to solve, & he was immediately intrigued, but on hearing the details had serious reservations.
Martin was barely featured in the book.
The film creates a story out of the relationship between Martin & Philomena. In the book, Martin is barely there. We don't hear about his life, his feelings, or his relationships with those involved.
TRUE-ISH
Philomena didn't recieve any visitors during her time at the Roscrea convent, her mother had died when she was little & her father told everybody she had gone away & nobody knew where she was. She had to work off her stay for three years though, not four.
TRUE
The girls had an hour a day to bond with their little ones, which made it all the more difficult for them when they were eventually taken away. Philomena's close friend in the convent had a little girl 6 months younger than Anthony, named Mary. The two children adored each other.
Margaret's daughter Mary was due to be adopted, much to Margaret's distress. Philomena was close to Sister Annunciata, who helped her throughout her time at the convent.
TRUE
Sister Annunciata smuggled in a box brownie to take photos of Anthony for Philomena, against convent rules. Philomena still has that photo.
Girls who gave birth in the convent had to pay £100 to be released, or else spend three years working there to pay their 'debt'.
TRUE-ISH
Majorie Hess arrived from America to adopt Mary. However, both mothers knew Mary & Anthony were due to be adopted together weeks before they were actually taken away. In the film it appears that Philomena was concerned only for her friend because at that point she didn't know Anthony was being taken too.
Not in the book.
This incident wasn't recorded in the book but it's likely Philomena would've been scolded for any misdemeanour.
Philomena wasn't able to see the new family in the nursery with Anthony & Mary.
Not in the book.
This incident wasn't recorded in the book.
TRUE
Mary's new family were won over by Anthony when he charmed them with his love for Mary.
Mary's adoptive family couldn't resist Anthony & decided to take him too.
TRUE
Philomena & Margaret found out through hearsay that their children were being taken, & ran to the window. Shouted & banged on it to get the children to look up, but they couldn't hear them. At the last minute Anthony looked round & they drove away.
TRUE-ISH
Philomena watched her son being taken away, & sobbed for weeks afterwards. However, she watched from an upstairs window, not the gate.
Philomena returned numerous times over the years but the nuns refused to help her, although they could have put her in touch with her son if they'd wanted to. Philomena & Martin did go to Ireland together to visit Roscrea.
FALSE-ISH
Martin went to Ireland to conduct most of his investigations alone, although they did visit Roscrea together at some point.
TRUE-ISH
Philomena remained a practising Catholic all her life.
TRUE
They visited the convent together.
Philomena was not bitter or angry about what happened to her, & thought everything happened for a reason.
TRUE
Martin & Philomena visited Roscrea together.
FALSE-ISH
Jane Russell did adopt an Irish baby, but from London, not Roscrea. We don't know much about Martin's specific actions, either, as he leaves himself mostly out of the book.
TRUE
Philomena did go back to Roscrea numerous times, searching for her son, and, once she knew he was dead, visiting his grave.
We don't know what Martin did exactly.
Although Martin did research the movie star Jane Russell's involvement with the convent, his specific actions were barely recorded in the book.
TRUE
Sister Hildegard admitted to destroying any incriminating documents herself.
We don't know what Martin did exactly.
Martin researched the convent & spoke to several nuns, but the details of his experience weren't recorded in the book.
Martin was barely featured in the book.
Martin's actions are barely in the book, this scene is not featured.
TRUE
Young girls did die in childbirth regularly. A girl named Mary Lawlor died aged 14 at Roscrea.
Philomena visited the abbey several times over the years, looking for her son, beginning the year he left. Each time they told her they had heard nothing, although on one occasion he had been there just three weeks previously. They insisted that she had signed a contract promising never to look for him, & must stick to her word. Philomena did sign such a contract, but the guilt, shame, helplessness & ignorance she experienced at the time prevented her from making a real choice.
TRUE
This was the case. Adoption records were destroyed, but the release papers were stored carefully.
Philomena was instilled with a great deal of guilt over her actions, which she carries to this day.
TRUE
Philomena was always kind about the nuns. Martin, Philomena & Jane met frequently during Martin's investigation.
TRUE-ISH
Jane Russell was one of many wealthy Americans who bought babies from Britain - she adopted a son from a Derry couple living in London. London produced passports for these babies no questions asked. It caused a scandal, & Russell had to fight to keep the child. While there wasn't officially a set fee, a 'donation' of a specific amount was recommended. The 'fire' at the abbey was indeed a bonfire set by Sister Hildegard in 1989, when she became worried after people started asking questions. She later confessed to destroying the records.
The business side of the process wasn't recorded in the book. But he likely pitched it to an editor.
TRUE-ISH
Martin went to Washington to find out more about Anthony once they knew he had died, but Philomena didn't go with him.
FALSE
Philomena didn't visit Washington with Martin.
TRUE
There is a photo of this event, shown in the book.
Martin flew to Washington to conduct his research.
FALSE
Philomena didn't visit Washington with Martin.
FALSE-ISH
Although Philomena doesn't seem to have expressed such doubts, her brother, who met Anthony at the convent & loved him, regretted that he didn't bring Anthony home & fretted over what might have become of him.
FALSE
Philomena didn't go to Washington.
Not in the book.
Martin barely appeared in the book, he kept himself out of the story.
FALSE-ISH
Philomena didn't go to Washington with Martin. Although she was thankful for him finding her son.
TRUE
Philomena remained a Catholic all her life, despite some wavering, & prayed for Anthony daily.
Not in the book.
Martin barely appeared in the book, he kept himself out of the story.
TRUE
Martin did search extensively for Anthony's records, researched his life for 4-5 years (some sources say 4, some 5).
FALSE
Philomena didn't accompany Martin to Washington.
TRUE-ISH
The adoptive parents had changed Anthony's name to Michael, & the family surname was Hess. He was a successful lawyer, & influential in his work with the Bush & Reagan administrations. He died from AIDS in 1995. However, it was Jane who discovered Anthony had died, not Martin. Jane researched Anthony before she contacted Martin for help.
FALSE
Philomena didn't accompany Martin to Washington. Jane had discovered that Anthony was dead before they got in touch with Martin..
Philomena didn't accompany Martin to Washington.
FALSE
FALSE-ISH
Philomena didn't accompany Martin to Washington. Martin & Philomena did correspond with other parties at various points to find out more about Anthony.
TRUE-ISH
Although Philomena didn't accompany Martin on the trip to America & there was no such photo, Martin did remember a lawyer by that name who he had met in Washington & connected the dots.
Martin corresponded with people who worked with Anthony on Philomena's behalf, including a female friend whom Anthony had been very close to - Nancy Hibbs. She confirmed his sexuality.
FALSE
Philomena didn't claim to have known her son was gay. She wasn't troubled or shocked by his sexuality, however, being comfortable with gay men after working with gay nurses throughout her career.
TRUE
Anthony & Pete lived together in an apartment in the city during the week, & in a country cottage at weekends.
Philomena expressed doubts about the story being published. She felt ashamed & guilty & afraid to tell the world her story.
FALSE-ISH
While Martin did correspond with Mary on Philomena's behalf, they did not visit her house, & she came across as warm & invested.
TRUE
Anthony did die of AIDS, in 1995. He had loved his adoptive mother, but struggled with his adoptive father, who was never sure about him & resisted any relationship.
There are photographs of Anthony playing as a baby.
TRUE-ISH
Philomena was a devout Catholic, but we don't know much about Martin's views on religion - he kept himself out of the book mostly.
Although Philomena didn't go to America, she was a devout Catholic & felt considerable guilt about her son.
Not in the book.
Although the business end of Martin's involvement in Philomena's story isn't in the book, it's reasonable to assume he had conversations with his publisher, Macmillan, at some point.
This incident isn't in the book, but Philomena was a devout Catholic who attended confession.
TRUE-ISH
Although Philomena did want the story published, she blamed herself for losing her son & continues to do so. She intially wanted real names kept out of it, but changed her mind. Her biggest regret was that she kept it a secret so long - perhaps if she had sought help sooner she could have met her son. The church instilled a shame in her that compelled her to keep her secret for decades.
FALSE
Steve Dallhof was willing to meet Philomena & discuss Anthony's life, flying over to England to do so.
Philomena didn't accompany Martin on his research trip. Pete, for his part, did want to see her & flew to London to meet with her several times.
TRUE
Anthony & Pete lived together in an apartment in the city during the week, & in a country cottage at weekends.
Not in the book.
This was a reference to the celtic ring that Anthony wore, but this flash of inspiration wasn't recorded in the book.
FALSE-ISH
Philomena didn't accompany Martin on the trip to London. However, although Anthony wasn't known to have worn a celtic pin, he did wear a celtic ring. Pete gave this to Philomena when they met, & she wears it every day.
FALSE
Martin & Philomena didn't visit Pete's house in the States. Rather, Pete flew to the UK & they met at Martin's home.
Pete was interested in meeting Philomena & open to knowing her.
FALSE
Philomena didn't visit Pete's home.
TRUE-ISH
Steve, Philomena, Martin & Jane met at Martin's London home in 2003, & several times subsequently, & talked about Anthony.
TRUE
Anthony did search for his mother. Steve took him on a final trip to the abbey following his AIDS diagnosis. Sister Hildegard lied to them, said she had no idea where Philomena was. Anthony asked to be buried there so that his mother could find him. Steve made a generous donation & made it happen.
Martin's feelings didn't feature in the book.
Martin's feelings & the relationship between him & Philomena didn't feature in the book.
Martin's thoughts & feelings, & his interactions with Philomena, were barely mentioned in the book.
FALSE-ISH
Martin, Philomena & Jane visited the abbey together, looking for the truth, but Sister Hildegard was dead by then, & Martin barely features in the book at all.
TRUE-ISH
This specific scene wasn't in the book, but Sister Hildegard did blame the girls for their unplanned pregnancies.
TRUE
While Martin was incredulous at what the church had done to Philomena, Philomena did not want to hold onto any anger.
Martin was barely featured in the book.
The film creates a story out of the relationship between Martin & Philomena. In the book, Martin is barely there. We don't hear about his life, his feelings, or his relationships with those involved.
TRUE
Anthony Lee (aka Michael Hess) asked for enough information to be put on his grave so that Philomena could find him. His message helped in the search.
TRUE-ISH
Originally Philomena wanted all names to be changed to protect the identities of those involved & keep herself anonymous, but changed her mind in the end. The figurine incicent wasn't in the book.
They did visit Roscrea together, & Philomena remained impressively positive about her experience, but this exact incident wasn't in the book.
TRUE
Martin published 'The Lost Child of Philomena Lee' in 2009.
Philomena has a large family. She visits Anthony's grave regularly & talks to him there.
TRUE
Martin does now work as a broadcaster & author.
-
Original Data Provided By:
Dr Stephanie Starling, David McCandless, DM
Omid Kashan, Karl Webster
Subtitles Compiled By:
BreadCodes