Original Data Provided By:
Dr Stephanie Starling, David McCandless, DM
Omid Kashan, Karl Webster
Subtitles Compiled By:
BreadCodes
-
TRUE
Lauda & Hunt entered the 1976 German Grand Prix at Nurburgring as prime rivals.
TRUE-ISH
Could be a reference to the time Hunt ended up in hospital after crashing his Mini on the roads. He had a beer at a local pub before going to hospital, where he was discharged a week later when the matron caught him in a 'compromising position' with a woman.
TRUE
Hunt was known for his love of women & partying. After having shared a flat with Hunt briefly, Lauda famously declared that he (Lauda) enjoyed sex as much as the next man, 'unless that man was James Hunt'.
Hunt did race at Crystal Palace in 1970.
TRUE
Hunt threw up before every race, regardless of who he was with or where he was. It was part of his pre-race ritual - nobody knows it if was nerves, excitement, or a hangover.
FALSE
Hunt didn't see Lauda at Crystal Palace in 1970, though. Lauda wasn't there.
Lauda didn't attend this race, & Hunt crashed out.
FALSE
Lauda wasn't present - they didn't race, they didn't meet.
TRUE
Lauda's family didn't mind him tinkering with engines & indulged his hobby, but were angry when they discovered he'd taken part in a race at Muhllacken. His father forbade him from racing ever again. Lauda raced again two weeks later & years of estrangement followed.
Lauda was able to get bank loans based on his family name, made plans to use the cash to buy his way in, since he wasn't getting the success needed to pull sponsorship.
TRUE
A helicopter arrived & took Lauda to hospital in Koblenz. His injuries were severe, & included third degree burns, broken ribs, collarbone & cheekbone, & complications from inhalation of toxic fumes.
FALSE-ISH
Hunt won second place at the Grovewood Awards, selected by the British Guild of Motoring Writers.
TRUE
Just one of Lauda's multiple bank loans covered the two million schillings required to race with BRM.
Things were going badly for Lauda when BRM's Louis Stanley got in touch.
TRUE
Lauda was brusque & demanding & didn't make a lot of friends.
Lauda knew his stuff, & suggested important modifications for the cars he raced over the years.
TRUE
BRM was broke & didn't have the funds for anything better than tinkering & second-hand parts.
FALSE-ISH
This sort-of happened at Ferrari, not BRM. Lauda told Mr. Ferrari that his car had too much understeer. Mr. Ferrari responded that Lauda had one week to lose a second from his lap time or he was out. Lauda modified the car & delivered, calling it 'a piece of cake, actually'.
TRUE
BRM offered Lauda a 2yr contract once they got wind of Ferrari's interest in the driver, hoping to tie him down. In the end, Ferrari paid off Lauda's contract & other debts to secure him for their team. Pretty much everybody Lauda ever spoke to was affronted in some way.
FALSE
Lauda had a serious girlfriend (Mariella Reininghaus) for years before meeting Marlene, who he married. He wasn't dating at this point. Although Hunt was a promiscuous fellow with swathes of female admirers, so he may well have dated the BRM track manager.
TRUE
Lord Hesketh bought a March 731 for Hunt, which premiered at the 1973 Monaco Grand Prix.
The American driver Mark Donohue died in an accident during a practise lap. Hunt saw it happen.
TRUE-ISH
The crash killed American driver Mark Donohue. Hunt threw up before every race, regardless of who he was with or where he was. It was part of his pre-race ritual. Whether or not he threw up at the exact moment he learnt of Donohue's death is unknown.
FALSE-ISH
Hunt was the more emotional of the pair, & Lauda was brutally honest, not afraid to air his views - such a scene isn't unlikely. Still, this moment wasn't in the Calley book.
This moment isn't in the Calley book.
It's pretty likely Hunt imagined his races by way of preparation, although this scene isn't in Calley's book.
TRUE-ISH
Hunt met Suzy while both were in Spain. They dated on & off, him resisting the commitment she wanted from him. Eventually he half-heartedly proposed.
TRUE
Hunt & Suzy were married in a lavish ceremony, paid for by Lord Hesketh. Hunt regretted his proposal & didn't want to go through with the wedding, but felt he couldn't let so many people down.
Ferrari were so keen to get Lauda on their team that they paid off his 2yr contract with BRM.
TRUE
Ferrari had the money & set-up, but hadn't won in years when Lauda joined. The cars weren't up to scratch, but the team owner wouldn't hear of it. Lauda confronted him in his usual foul language & was met with a threat. Ultimately though the cars were improved.
Regazzoni walked out of BRM to join Ferrari, & told them Lauda should be his teammate. Ferrari had noticed Lauda's strong performances in weak cars & headhunted him, paying off his contract with BRM so he could join the team.
TRUE
Lauda & Regazzoni always had a good relationship.
TRUE-ISH
Lauda met Marlene at a party she threw with her boyfriend. They bonded straight away, & both left their partners to be with one another. Marriage quickly followed.
FALSE
The whole hitch-hiking scene was made up.
Lauda was a superstar in his home country of Austria, & had a huge following in Italy. The hitch-hiking scene never happened, though.
FALSE
The whole hitch-hiking scene was made up.
TRUE
Niki Lauda was the 1975 F1 world champion. He won with Ferrari.
TRUE-ISH
Although Lauda was a great test driver & knew a lot about cars, he didn't design the suspension as suggested in the film. He had a lot of mechanical input in general, though.
TRUE
Team Hesketh folded when the money ran out.
Lord Hesketh had initally hoped to avoid sponsorship at all, citing it as crude. Still, in dire straits he chased £300,000 of sponsorship cash the team needed to stay afloat, to no avail. The team fell apart.
TRUE
Following his most successful F1 season & first victory, financial disaster meant Hunt found himself with no car & no team.
Hesketh was unable to attract sponsorship for Hunt, & eventually, they ran out of cash.
TRUE
Suzy was a supportive wife, despite his neglect & consistent unfaithfulness. He later admitted he never loved her.
Hunt got a call from Emerson Fittipaldi's manager, telling him Fittipaldi was leaving McLaren to joint his brother's team & a space would be opening up.
TRUE
McLaren took Hunt on.
McLaren boss Teddy Mayer certainly did find Hunt to be a loose cannon, & was embarrased by his antics. Still, Hunt was a winner & did well with McLaren.
TRUE
Hunt & Lauda were both top of their game, & remained each other's only true competitors throughout the season.
Brazilian Grand Prix, 25th Jan 1976: Lauda won, qualified second. Hunt retired due to throttle issues.
TRUE
South African Grand Prix, 6th Mar 1976: Lauda won, qualified second. Hunt came second.
Spanish Grand Prix, 2nd May 1976: Lauda qualified 2nd, finished 2nd. Hunt won, but was disqualified when it was found that his car was 1.8cm wider than regulations allowed.
TRUE
Monaco Grand Prix, 30th May 1976: Lauda won, Hunt crashed & retired.
Belgian Grand Prix, 16th May 1976: Lauda won, Hunt qualified 3rd, retired to due gearbox issues.
TRUE
McLaren repositioned the oil coolers to bring the car back in-line with regulations, but the modifications were disastrous. Lauda was partially to blame for Hunt's disqualification - he appeared in court to give evidence against him.
Hunt's marriage to Suzy Miller broke down following her affair with Richard Burton in 1976.
TRUE
Suzy finally left Hunt for Burton, but they had been privately estranged for some time & the split came as a relief to Hunt.
When questioned by the press about Suzy's affair he shrugged it off & claimed the Grand Prix had his full focus. After meeting with his wife in New York, he dropped her off at Burton's hotel, heightening the scandal.
TRUE
Hunt was known for his 'charm' & hooked up with women everywhere he went. He had a thing for air stewardesses, who often shared his hotel rooms.
French Grand Prix, 4th Jul 1976, Lauda retired with engine failure, Hunt won.
TRUE
British Grand Prix, 18th Jul 1976, Lauda won, Hunt second but disqualified.
The FIA heard Hunt's case & decided to revoke the disqualification on the grounds that an extra 1.8cm width would not have given him an unfair advantage. The decision propelled Hunt forwards, giving him an additional 9 points for the season.
TRUE-ISH
Hunt & Lauda were both arrogant & self-assured, but this piece of dialogue isn't in Calley's book.
TRUE
Lauda & Marlene were married soon after they met, to much controversy. He was the practical type through & through.
FALSE-ISH
Little is known about Lauda & Marlene's wedding, it was done in secret & came as a surprise to the public. Lauda wasn't into extravagance in any aspect of his life.
TRUE
Lauda & Marlene were very close.
FALSE-ISH
Lauda & Marlene were, & continue to be, very private people. Details like this aren't known. Lauda recently said of his latest marriage, 'I want to protect my private life & not carry it out in detail as Boris Becker does.'
TRUE
Ernst Raetz was killed at Nurburgring during practice on Jul 9th, 1976.
No record of this.
There's no record of a fan saying this to Lauda, although he signed plenty of autographs.
TRUE
The Nurburgring track in Germany is renowned as one of the toughest in the world. & it was drenched that day.
TRUE-ISH
Lauda wasn't always so risk-averse, but a bad accident at Zolder spurred him to take a safer, analytical approach to racing. Lauda did call a meeting before the race, insisting that the track & conditions were too dangerous. He was outvoted by one. Hunt didn't sway the vote though. The majority of the drivers wanted to race.
TRUE
All the drivers bar one, Jochen Mass, started the race on wet weather tyres.
Hunt & Lauda started next to each other, Hunt's car on pole position.
TRUE
The drivers stopped to change their tyres, giving Jochen Mass, who'd picked the right tyres in the first place, a significant lead. Lauda hit the track desperate to catch Hunt.
Lauda's Ferrari hit the banking just before the Bergwerk corner & burst into flames. The three drivers he collided with, Guy Edwards, Harold Ertl & Brett Lunger, all stopped & tried to drag Lauda from the burning car.
TRUE
A German newspaper photographed Lauda in a coma, & ran the headline 'My God, Where Is His Face?'.
During the week following the accident, a priest visited to give him the last rites. The build up of fluid in Lauda's lungs was so dangerous that nobody thought he would survive.
TRUE
Hunt reported that he felt totally hopeless following the accident, but sent Lauda a provocative telegram, hoping to spark his fighting spirit.
Marlene went straight to the hospital before she even knew which of the 28 drivers had crashed. Lauda woke up against all expectations. She remained with him through his recovery.
TRUE
Lauda had some reconstruction & numerous skin grafts, but severe scarring & deformation remained. Marlene fainted when she first saw his face after the accident.
Lauda watched Grand Prix races from his hospital bed, including the Austrian Grand Prix, which was almost cancelled out of respect for Lauda.
TRUE
Lauda's lungs were so badly damaged they had to be vacuumed. He was in such a terrible state that his doctors put his survival down to pure will.
TRUE-ISH
We don't know much about the private moments between Marlene & Lauda, but he has said the pain of the crash helmet was 'unbearable', & his wounds seeped through his balaclava during his first post-accident race at Monza.
TRUE
Lauda only missed two races of that season, returning to race at Monza 6 weeks after the priest gave him last rites. He was still wrapped in bandages, which were bloodsoaked by the end of the race.
FALSE
Hunt had no part to play in Lauda's accident. While the film showed Hunt persuading the majority of the drivers to go ahead with the race that day, in reality, it was a close call that Lauda lost by one vote.
Although Hunt did have reputation for being wild, this incident isn't on record. Hunt's son Tom has said it was possible, though - 'that's the way dad was'.
TRUE
People were shocked to see him return to racing at all, never mind so soon. Fingers were crossed for him.
Lauda made a slow start, but managed to finish fourth after Laffite, Regazzoni & Peterson.
TRUE-ISH
A reporter at a press conference did ask Lauda if he thought his marriage would survive his facial disfigurement, & whether he planned to have plastic surgery. Lauda reacted angrily, stating he did not care how he looked.
Lauda's return to the track was seen as heroic by contemporaries, particularly as he was seen peeling blood soaked bandages from raw wounds afterwards. He wasn't lifted by the crowd, though.
TRUE
The weather was horrendous on that day, the rain so heavy there were streams running across the track. Many were concerned & some drivers wanted the race cancelled.
Hunt was a nervous driver with a crippling fear of failure, but always outwardly confident, while Lauda took a calm, matter-of-fact approach to racing - nothing much scared him.
TRUE
At the time F1 races were rarely televised in the UK, but the Japan Mount Fuji race was due to be shown live on October 24th, 1976.
The weather was horrendous on that day, the rain so heavy there were streams running across the track.
TRUE
Hunt did have holes drilled into his visor as part of the preparation for the race in Japan. The original hand drill used was auctioned off in 2014.
Hunt & Lauda respected one another a great deal, & admired each other's skill.
TRUE
The spray virtually blinded Lauda. His eyelids were so badly burnt he struggled to blink, & his damaged tear ducts caused excessive watering. He pulled in, prioritising his safety.
The Ferrari team were all over the car, anxious to find out what was wrong. Lauda filled them in.
TRUE
The Ferrari team were willing to blame Lauda's exit on a mechanical issue, but he insisted on the truth. 3 other drivers pulled out for safety reasons during the race.
Hunt failed to pull in for tyre changes, hoping to gain on the other drivers as they did so. By the time he finally entered the pitstop his tyres had disintegrated.
FALSE-ISH
Hunt was furious that his team had messed up his tyre strategy, costing him precious time. It took 27 seconds to change all 4 tyres. No record of them suggesting he give up, though.
TRUE
The pit board was faulty & as Hunt finished the race, he had no idea he had won the championship.
Hunt insisted on examining the race charts himself, before accepting his win.
TRUE
Today, Lauda says he would not have changed anything, has no regrets. He claims it was stupid for anybody to race that day. He only did the single lap he completed so that Ferrari would get their money.
Unlike Lauda the year before, Hunt achieved celebrity status with his championship victory, & partied hard in the aftermath.
FALSE-ISH
Lauda took an interest in planes for practical reasons, since he travelled so much, but it became a passion. He bought a Cessna Golden Eagle & learnt to fly. We don't know if Hunt & Lauda met up in an aircraft hanger, though.
There's no record of Hunt & Lauda meeting up in an aircraft hanger, although they did remain friends.
TRUE
Hunt & Lauda were good friends, & respected one another. Hunt described Lauda as fair & tough. Hunt became a broadcaster for the BBC. Lauda became world champion for the last time in 1984, his third championship.
-
Original Data Provided By:
Dr Stephanie Starling, David McCandless, DM
Omid Kashan, Karl Webster
Subtitles Compiled By:
BreadCodes