Original Data Provided By:
Dr Stephanie Starling, David McCandless, DM
Omid Kashan, Karl Webster
Subtitles Compiled By:
BreadCodes
-
TRUE
King was awarded the Nobel Peace Prize in Oslo, December 10th 1964.
Members of the Ku Klux Klan bombed the 16th Street Baptist Church on Sunday September 15th, 1963. Four little girls were killed, 22 people were injured.
TRUE
Annie Lee Cooper was denied the right to vote on her 5th attempt because she couldn't name the 67 county judges in Alabama, a real requirement meant to keep blacks from registering.
TRUE-ISH
Johnson wasn't a fan of King or his methods. Still, some argue that Johnson's role as something of an adversary in the movie is inaccurate, that he was considerably more supportive than shown. White was indeed a trusted aide.
Although some have said the meeting wasn't as confrontational in real life as it was portrayed in the movie, this was pretty much exactly how the conversation went. King wanted a voting rights bill, Johnson promised to do it eventually but had more politically expedient priorities.
TRUE
After King's conversation with Johnson, he headed to Selma with Nash, Abernathy, Young & Orange.
James Bevel was a member of the SCLC, & was at King's side in Selma.
TRUE
Black leaders checked in for a night at the whites-only Hotel Albert, where a leader of the National States' Rights Party knocked him to floor & kicked him.
Hoover worked tirelessly to discredit King, attempting to link him to the Communist party, tracking him & tapping his phone. The FBI threatened to leak tapes that suggest King was having affairs to the public.
TRUE
Coretta Scott King received many phone calls, usually threatening her husband's life. Naturally she was concerned, but has said she felt they were part of something greater than themselves.
Mahalia Jackson was a gospel singer. She travelled with King & the SCLC, & sang before King's 'I Have a Dream' speech. King was enamoured by her voice.
TRUE
Richie Jean Jackson opened her home to the Selma protesters, including KING & SCLC activists. Her house became an unofficial HQ for the movement.
There was major tension between the SCLC & the SNCC. SNCC prioritised grassroots organising, & didn't trust the SCLC's highly visual attention-grabbing tactics.
TRUE
The Selma Voting Rights Campaign officially began Jan 2nd 1965, when King gave a speech at Brown Chapel A.M.E. Church, encouraging people to dem & their right to vote.
We couldn't find a source for this.
We couldn't find a source for this, but from records of King's speeches it sounds like the kind of thing he'd say.
TRUE
In his autobiography James Forman describes the movement's tactics - Sheriff Jim Clark could be counted on to incite violence against the protesters, thus drawing sympathy for the movement.
King led over 100 protesters to the county courthouse in non-violent demonstration.
TRUE
The protest was a peaceful sit-in.
TRUE-ISH
Cooper joined the sit-in, & hit Clark after he twisted her arm & threw her to the ground. Jimmie Lee Jackson's family weren't actually present there, but were part of a march in nearby Marion, where Cager was hit over the head by a state trooper.
TRUE
King was arrested along with dozens of others. He made a conscious effort to be arrested for publicity, & refused to post bond.
Gov. Wallace was already known as a tyrannical bigot, & was seen as out of control by Johnson & his advisors.
TRUE-ISH
Although we can't find a source for what they talked about in jail, King did suffer moments of despondency during his civil rights work.
TRUE
Malcolm X responded to King being attacked in the hotel by issuing a threat against violent racists. He was invited to Browm Chapel A.M.E. to give a talk, which SCLC initially wanted to block.
Coretta Scott King met with Malcolm X in secret. In a 1988 interview, she described the conversation just as it was in the movie, & said it made her feel optimistic that he & King could work together.
TRUE
TRUE-ISH
We don't know if King & his wife had this exact conversation while he was in jail, but King was suspicious of Malcolm X & deplored his violent approach.
TRUE
Wallace had plans to bring the movement down. He sanctioned extra violence against the black protesters, authorized by J. Edgar Hoover, then FBI director. King had bailed himself out of jail at this point.
The police turned off the streetlights to conceal their violence from reporters, & attacked. Jimmie Lee Jackson, along with his mother & grandfather, fled the scene.
TRUE-ISH
The family fled but the police found them, beat Cager Lee. Jimmie Lee Jackson stepped in & was shot by state trooper JB Fowler. Jackson lived for 8 days before dying of an infection following the shooting. Fowler was convicted of second-degree manslaughter in 2010.
TRUE
King did visit Jimmie Lee Jackson & his family in the hospital.
Jackson's death inspired a milestone speech from King, sparking the first Selma to Montgomery march.
TRUE
King & the SCLC & SNCC met frequently for strategy meetings during the Selma action.
TRUE-ISH
King informed Johnson of his intention to use Selma to bring attention to injustices in black voter registration. While it is contested whether Johnson was in support of the march or not, he did delay the legislation King wanted.
We couldn't find a source for this.
There were numerous threats to King's life, but we couldn't find a source for the details of such a conversation between White  & King's people.
TRUE-ISH
King met with Johnson for an hour & a half to discuss legislation, but available details of the meeting aren't extensive & we don't know exactly what was said.
Johnson worked closely with Hoover as FBI director & they would have met often to discuss King & the Civil Rights Movement, although there is fierce controversy over whether or not Johnson backed Hoover's vendetta against King.
TRUE
Hoover tracked King & tapped his phone. Those tapes are sealed by court order until 2027, but it's said that at least two suggest King was having affairs, & the FBI threatened to leak them to the public. The FBI did mail incriminating tapes to King's wife.
We couldn't find a source for this.
King did stay away the first day of the march, although we don't know if it was to be with Coretta specifically.
TRUE
Wallace ordered Highway Patrol to use 'whatever measures are necessary to prevent a march'. Leaders like Bevel attended workshops & learnt nonviolence techniques, passing them on to protesters. Clark put out a call for all white males over 21 to be deputised ready to fight.
SNCC had reservations about the march, especially when they found out King wouldn't be there on the first day. They allowed Lewis to participate, though, & provided logistical support.
TRUE
John Lewis & Hosea Williams led more than 500 marchers across Edmund Pettus Bridge.
Alabama state troopers awaited the protesters on the other side of the bridge.
TRUE-ISH
Footage from the march was broadcast on CBS but we don't know if Bayard called Young.
TRUE
Troopers gave a warning to disband. March leaders asked to talk, but were silenced. Troopers on horseback used nightsticks & tear gas to attack the protesters.
TRUE-ISH
Millions of people viewed events on CBS that day. We don't know if King watched but we presume so.
TRUE
Amelia Boynton was assaulted by the troopers. A photograph of her knocked to the ground was printed in internationally.
Millions of people viewed events on CBS that day.
We couldn't find a source for this.
We can't find a source to state whether Lewis & Abernathy personally helped Boynton, although this type of cameraderie was not unusual among the movement's supporters & leaders.
TRUE
The marchers returned to the chapel to reconvene.
TRUE-ISH
Although we don't know if this specific conversation happened, we do know the leaders discouraged all violence.
TRUE
King led 2000 people in a second, symbolic march across Edmund Pettus Bridge in response to Bloody Sunday.
King put out a call for supporters, especially ministers of all faiths, to come to Selma.
TRUE
James Reeb, a Universalist Minister from Boston, had seen the violence of Bloody Sunday on the news, & answered King's call to ministers of all faiths to come to Selma in support. His wife didn't want him to go.
While Judge Johnson was sympathetic, he issued a restraining order against the march until proper procedure had been followed in the form of court hearings.
We couldn't find a source for this.
We don't have records of any such conversation between the president & his aide.
TRUE
Doar met with King at Jackson's house, urged him to postpone the march. SCLC leadership told Doar that wasn't going to happen.
Archibishop Iakovos marched arm-in-arm with King from Selma - a photo of that moment made it to Life Magazine's front cover. Liuzzo & Reeb were there too, plus a bunch of other white people standing alongside the black protesters.
TRUE
A considerably minority of the protesters were white, & the gathering included ministers from many faiths.
King led a symbolic march across the bridge after the events of Bloody Sunday. On the bridge, the marchers kneeled to pray.
TRUE
King turned the marchers back. They needed federal protection if they were to continue safely to Montgomery, & didn't want to break their restraining order & risk losing favour with a judge sympathetic to their cause.
Florida governor LeRoy Collins had suggested a compromise between Doar's urging not to march at all & the movement's insistence on marching. It was his idea to lead protesters symbolically to the bridge before turning around. Only a handful were let in on the plan, & many participants were confused & let down.
TRUE
King wrote numerous letters to his wife.
TRUE-ISH
Reeb & two other men were attacked by 3 white men & beaten with clubs, after they were seen eating at an integrated diner in Selma. Reeb died two days later, not at the scene as portrayed in the movie.
TRUE
Seven Selma activists sat-in at the White House & were arrested. Several others tried but were stopped. Johnson wasn't impressed, but the activists told him to act faster if he wanted to prevent such inconveniences.
We couldn't find a source for this.
We couldn't find a source for this conversation, but we know there were discussions on tactics between the various leaders of the movement.
TRUE
King went to court to win the right for his supporters to march safely from Selma to Montgomery in protest of unlawful restrictions on black voter registration.
Judge Frank Johnson overturned Gov. Wallace's prohibition of the march.
TRUE
A 'Stars for Freedom' concert was held at Montgomery. Performers included Nina Simone, Tony Bennett, Sammy Davis Jr. & many others.
Johnson tried to work with Wallace so as not to upset the State's Rights movement, but eventually went over his head & committed to protecting the marchers.
TRUE
Johnson met with Wallace to urge him to use the military at his disposal to protect the marchers. His response isn't favourable.
Johnson convened a joint session of Congress & demanded they pass his new Voting Rights Bill.
TRUE
John Doar was a lawyer & assistant attorney general for civil rights from 1960 to 1967. He was in Montgomery the day the march arrived there to protect King. He advised the movement on safety.
8000 people completed the march from Selma to Montgomery. They marched with military protection.
TRUE
Titles are all accurate. Many of the activists had successful careers. Some were murdered. Johnson introduced the Voting Rights Act of 1965 to congress days after the march.
-
Original Data Provided By:
Dr Stephanie Starling, David McCandless, DM
Omid Kashan, Karl Webster
Subtitles Compiled By:
BreadCodes