Original Data Provided By:
Dr Stephanie Starling, David McCandless, DM
Omid Kashan, Karl Webster
Subtitles Compiled By:
BreadCodes
-
TRUE-ISH
Geoghan was accused of molestation several times & was moved around the parishes, & sent to a paedophile treatment centre. His behaviour was covered up by the church & his victims' families told to keep quiet. The police were involved, although details are unclear.
We don't know if a reporter retired in 2001.
TRUE
A new editor, Marty Baron, was hired from the Miami Herald in 2001.
FALSE
The director chose to play on the insider/outsider dynamic, putting tension between the Bostonians & new guy Baron. In reality, Baron was accepted just fine, & respected by Robinson, Bradlee etc.
TRUE
Bradlee & Robinson worked closely together, & were curious to see what outsider Baron would bring.
FALSE-ISH
There were several meetings between Baron & the staff although there wasn't the tension between them as shown in the movie.
TRUE
Baron's interest was peaked by McNamara's column, published the week before he started at The Globe, that reported Garabedian's accusation that Law had known about Geoghan's behaviour. Baron likely sat down with her about the piece.
Baron put the Spotlight team on the Geoghan story on his very first day as editor in 2001. The documents relating to the case were under a confidentiality seal granted to church lawyers.
TRUE
Baron put the team on the Geoghan case on his first day.
Spotlight had just finished a big story & were considering what to take on next when Baron asked them to do some digging on Geoghan, see if there was a bigger story there.
TRUE
The team split up possible witnesses so that each reporter had their own set of people to interview.
Pfeiffer's grandmother was a devout catholic. She always carried a rosary, & despite the revelations, attended church until the day she died.
TRUE
The team went through loads of old clips during their research.
FALSE-ISH
It's unclear whether Baron literally got lost in the Globe offices, but that scene represents his outsiderness - 'I knew virtually nobody at the paper & virtually nobody in town', he states.
TRUE
After getting 50/50 odds from the Globe's lawyer on their chances of winning the suit, Baron asked publisher Gilman to approve them going to court. He tentatively agreed it was the right thing to do.
Garabedian represented most of the victims. The office was shabby & didn't have a receptionist, Garabedian wasn't well-known or well-off.
TRUE
Spotlight did meet with Macleish. Garabedian ran a single-attorney law firm dealing exclusively with victims of sexual abuse. He has been praised as the quintessential little guy singlehandedly taking on the Catholic Church. He was always up against it.
Garabedian was suspicious of The Globe, thought they were controlled by the church, or that they might publish a sensational story that would exploit his clients without helping them. He watched Rezendes interview his clients for days before he came around.
TRUE
Searching through old clips was part of the process.
FALSE
Spotlight turned to SNAP for help tracking down victims. Through this national organisation they found victims, & some of their lawyers, who put them in touch with further victims & so on.
TRUE
Bradlee was known for being a bulldog, & wanted things done right. He was a major baseball fan, & spent ten years writing a biography of Ted Williams, so he was at a lot of Fenway Park games.
FALSE-ISH
Sullivan was a composite character, representing 6 lawyers the Spotlight team consulted. We don't have details of their conversations.
TRUE
The filmmakers did some serious digging into the mundane aspects of the reporters' real lives, they went after authenticity in a big way.
Bradlee & others were concerned about the impact of the story on the readership. Circulation was declining anyway & publishing a huge scandal about the church could alienate The Globe's Catholic readership. In the end they decided it was too important not to go ahead.
FALSE-ISH
Baron did visit Law's residence as part of meeting people in the community. They mostly talked about the Middle East. The meeting wasn't as meaningful as it's portrayed in the film, though. Law did give Baron a gift of sorts.
TRUE-ISH
As Baron left the meeting Law took a copy of the Catechism from his shelf & handed it to him. It wasn't wrapped or anything.
TRUE
Saviano did talk extensively with the Spotlight team.
Saviano sent all the information he had to The Globe 5 years previously, but little happened. Although he has said he doesn't remember being as angry as he is portrayed to be, friends of his from the time have told him yeah, you were pretty angry back then.
TRUE
Saviano & his organisation SNAP were committed to stopping child-abuse by priests, so he had a significant agenda. Still, he was informed & had a lot of contacts.
Garabedian was concerned that The Globe would exploit his clients for a good story. Eventually Rezendes persuaded him that giving them a voice mattered. Rezendes has described his role as 'schmoozing' Garabedian.
TRUE
Pfeiffer did interview Joe Crowley.
Patrick McSorely was abused by Father Geoghan. He told his story to the Spotlight team.
TRUE
Joe Crowley was abused by Father Shanley. Pfeiffer did press for specifics, she felt 'molest' was too clinical a word.
Geoghan visited McSorely's home after his father died to offer condolences. He offered to take McSorely, then 12, for ice cream. He molested McSorely in the car & told him to keep it secret. McSorely struggled with substance abuse & depression & died aged 29.
TRUE
Crowley struggled with alcohol abuse for years after being raped by Father Shanley & abused by him & others. The day Shanley was convicted was the day Crowley reached his 9th year of sobriety.
Many of the abuse victims killed themselves, or tried to. McSorely died at 29 two years after the story was published. The cause of death wasn't released, but suspected to be an overdose.
TRUE
Pfeiffer was very thorough, & followed up for details. Unclear whether Crowley spoke to Macleish about his case, but Crowley has praised the film's accuracy, so it's likely true.
Judge Sweeney did agree to hear on the sealed documents motion.
TRUE
The archdiocese settled around 50 lawsuits against Geoghan between 1997 & 2002.
Bradlee was nervous about the whole thing, but agreed to expanding the investigation.
TRUE
Richard Sipe, a former monk-priest, worked at a treatment centre for paedophile priests. He was a qualified psychotherapist who conducted a major study into the issue of sexual abuse within the Catholic Church. He cooperated with The Globe's investigation.
The team were trying to figure out how they could track down every priest who had been accused of abuse.
TRUE
The Globe had thousands of pages of parish directories in their library.
The Catholic Church repeatedly tried to discredit Sipe & his research.
TRUE
They found that several of the priests accused of abuse had been designated statuses like 'sick leave', 'awaiting assignment' etc. It raised suspicions.
The archdiocese settled around 50 lawsuits against Geoghan between 1997 & 2002. No documents relating to these cases were made public.
TRUE
Robinson sat down with MacLeish to question him on the settlements.
At this point they thought 12 or 13 priests was the height of the story.
FALSE
Conley was a fabricated person, a 'fixer' for the church who represented the various people involved in covering up for abusive priests.
TRUE
Robinson did go to BC High & was an important alumnus.
Garabedian continues to assert that it takes a village to abuse a child.
FALSE-ISH
Sullivan was a composite character, representing 6 lawyers the Spotlight team consulted. We don't have details of their conversations.
TRUE
They found that several of the priests accused of abuse had been designated statuses like 'sick leave', 'awaiting assignment' etc. It raised suspicions.
6% is in line with the paeodophile figures in the general population, & was the figure Sipe suggested, yet 10% of priests in the Boston archdiocese were  accused of molesting children. A report predicted paedophilia would cost the church $1bn.
TRUE
The Spotlight team decided to speak to as many victims as possible, hoping to identify the names of the 90 or so priests they now expected to have committed sexual abuse.
Robinson came up with this idea in a lightbulb moment. They took note of various 'on-the-shelf' designations.
TRUE
The team searched through 17 years' worth of parish directories. They describe it as incredibly tedious, like reading thousands of pages from the phone book. It took them 3 weeks.
FALSE-ISH
The church used a house in Milton to house 'on-the-shelf' priests. It was only a quarter-mile from Robinson's house (not Carroll's).
TRUE
Carroll was a data guy. He set up a spreadsheet, where all priests with suspicious designations in the parish directories were collated. They had 87 to follow up on at this stage.
FALSE-ISH
Sullivan was a composite character, representing 6 lawyers the Spotlight team consulted. We don't have details of their conversations.
Robinson did speak with MacLeish about the story. MacLeish refusing to see them isn't on the record, though.
FALSE-ISH
The team did talk to MacLeish about the story, but it was the filmmakers who discovered that MacLeish had sent a list of names to The Globe when they came across some clips & spoke to MacLeish themselves.
TRUE
Rezendes spoke at length to Richard Sipe, who warned them about the power of the church.
Team members met frequently, they worked around the clock. They were all distressed by what they uncovered. Robinson's wife, a nurse, thought they all had PTSD.
TRUE-ISH
We don't know if this conversation happened in this way, but the reporters have talked about their feelings of guilt around not questioning the church sooner.
TRUE
Baron didn't want just individual abuse stories reported, he wanted the systemic cover-up exposed - he thought that approach would have the best chance of affecting change.
FALSE
The church used a house in Milton to house 'on-the-shelf' priests. It was only a quarter-mile from Robinson's house (not Carroll's).
TRUE
The team had doors slammed in their faces, calls cut. Many more were amenable, though.
TRUE-ISH
Paquin did admit his crimes to Pfeiffer when she interviewed him. He 'fooled around' with boys for 15yrs. He was raped by a Catholic priest himself as a teen. However, it wasn't a doorstep confession. He admitted his crimes across 2 interviews.
FALSE
No record of Paquin's sister being involved like this. Paquin was interviewed twice & was cooperative.
TRUE-ISH
The Globe did go to court to get the full set of documents relating to abuse cases against priests undealed. The court session was so under-the-radar that Rezendes was the only journalist who attended.
TRUE
There were numerous abuse cases at BC High, the school Robinson went to.
Garabedian came under fire from the church, who took every opportunity to weaken his case against them.
TRUE
Garabedian had filed documents as part of motions that then became public. Out of fear of the church's retribution he didn't leak them to the press, just hoped a reporter would find them. When by August 2001 this hadn't happened, he tipped off Rezendes.
Garabedian had filed 14 sets of documents, all were missing from the docket file at the courthouse.
TRUE
Globe attorney Anthony Fuller asked Judge Sweeney to order the documents re-filed.
The attacks delayed the Spotlight team's research & the story's publication for 8 weeks.
TRUE
The Globe had a special interest in the 9/11 story, since the flights that hit the Trade Center had originated in Boston. They were super busy with it, & it worried the Spotlight team that they had to put their story aside.
FALSE-ISH
There was concern that other papers would access the documents before Spotlight were ready to print their story, but Rezendes didn't ask Garabedian to delay. The documents were sent to him in Florida.
TRUE-ISH
Saviano didn't have that meeting with Pfeiffer in a restaurant, but he did write a letter to the Globe, complaining about the 8-week 9/11 delay.
FALSE-ISH
Garabedian did re-file the documents, but it wasn't this dramatic. Rezendes had Globe attorney Fuller send the documents to him by courier while he was in Florida.
Robinson was editor of the section that had published that clip years before. However, this scene where Pfeiffer hands him the piece didn't happen.
FALSE-ISH
Carroll was weighed down by it all, the whole team struggled emotionally with the story. He didn't have a picture of the treatment centre on his fridge though, & besides, it wasn't down the road from him but from Robinson.
TRUE
Kevin (real name Jim Scanlan) had never told anybody about Father Talbot's abuse before he spoke to Robinson.
FALSE
Rezendes didn't get the documents direct from the courthouse. Rather, the Globe's attorney got copies sent to Rezendes by courier.
TRUE-ISH
This meeting did happen, although Conley wasn't a real person. Dunn has spoken out against his characterisation in the film. He claims he never tried to minimise the victims' suffering or cover up the abuse. However, he did say they didn't know anything.
Conley wasn't a real person, & Dunn has called out the filmmakers for portraying him as a bad guy. Still, Spotlight suspected BC High, along with the police, lawmakers, politicians etc of covering for the Catholic Church.
TRUE
Judge Volterra did question The Globe's motives, asserting that these were sensitive documents. Rezendes argued that they would be handled responsibly.
FALSE
This didn't happen, & the real Rezendes has said he wouldn't have forked out over $80 to use a copier.
TRUE
A letter from Bishop John D'Arcy to Cardinal Law, written in 1984 after Law had reassigned Geoghan, proved that Law knew about Geoghan's abuse of young boys. D'Arcy objected to Law's decision because of Geoghan's known history.
Bishop D'Arcy wrote in protest at Geoghan's reassignment to Weston. He suggested Geoghan work only weekends while receiving therapy.
TRUE-ISH
The Spotlight team debated whether to publish the documents they got from Garabedian right away, or to wait until they had the full story. Waiting made Rezendes nervous, but he didn't blow up over it.
TRUE
Pfeiffer found the story emotionally taxing, particularly interviewing one abuse victim after another.
Rezendes was a lapsed Catholic, but had thought that he would go back to the church some day. Following his discoveries about the abuse cover-ups, he couldn't even consider going back, it was 'too shattering'.
FALSE
Conley was a fabricated person, a 'fixer' for the church who represented the various people involved in covering up for abusive priests.
TRUE
Judge Constance M. Sweeney ordered the documents be made public.
The archdiocese appealed to the state Appeals Court, arguing that the public shouldn't have access to info about the church's inner workings. The appeal was denied.
TRUE
The Spotlight team debated whether to publish the documents they got from Garabedian right away, or to wait until they had the full story. They decided they wanted to present a comprehensive picture of the scandal to debute the series, so they waited.
They were getting the article drafted throughout December, & had been asking Law for a quote since mid-month.
TRUE
The team worked around the clock to get all the threads of the story together in time for their new year publication date. Carroll described himself at the time as a 'puddle' - exhausted.
FALSE-ISH
Sullivan was a composite character, representing 6 lawyers the Spotlight team consulted. We don't have details of their conversations.
TRUE
The Globe requested interviews with Law several times between Dec 2001 & publishing their story in Jan 2002. At the last minute, Law's PR person called back.
The Globe requested interviews with Law several times between Dec 2001 & publishing their story in Jan 2002. He would not even accept questions in writing, & claimed to have no interest in what they might be.
TRUE-ISH
It was the beginning of the online age when The Globe broke the story, so posting links to evidence was still pretty novel. Data geek Matt Carroll knew how to do stuff like that. Sullivan was a composite character, representing 6 lawyers.
The dept. that published the story Macleish handed them in 1993 was run by Robinson at the time. Come 2012, when the film was being made, the director brought this up after doing some digging. Robinson had no memory of that particular story.
TRUE
Law did call Baron, told him he had no comment.
Thousands of copies were printed. Circulation was over 800,000 for the Sunday paper.
TRUE
Pfeiffer's grandmother was 'shocked & saddened' by the revelations. She stuck with the church until her death, though.
Several victims sought Garabedian out for help following the Globe's publication of the story. The woman shown might have represented one such client, Ms. MacPherson, who was raped & abused by a priest from the age of 4. She now has two children.
FALSE
Robinson isn't on record saying he literally watched the trucks roll out.
FALSE-ISH
Church allowed abuse by priest for years' was the heading of the breaking story. Many others followed. There was a treament centre near Robinson's apartment, but not near Carroll's. Whether Carroll, or Robinson, dropped a paper off there isn't on record.
Although he wasn't writing a novel, Carroll, along with Globe colleagues, wrote a book about the paedophilia in the Catholic Church, published the same year as the Globe story. It's been described as a horror.
TRUE
They were there around the clock, fully invested in the story & reactions to it.
The team were surprised by the lack of backlash. They put it down to the quality of the evidence they used, the fact that they were able to link readers to copies of genuine letters from bishops etc. The tipline was busy with victims calling in, though.
TRUE
The Spotlight team interviewed 30 or 40 victims during their research. Once the story broke, a further 300 from the Boston archdiocese reported being abused as children.
The Globe worked solidly on the story for around a year & a half, publishing everything they found.
TRUE
249 priests molested children in Boston over several decades. The church shuffled these priests from parish to parish to cover up their crimes.
The Vatican gave Law a distinguished post in Rome in 2002 after public outrage & a petition by 58 priests demanded he resign.
TRUE
In 2014 the Vatican said it had defrocked 848 priests worldwide for sexual abuse between 2004 & 2013 alone, & 2572 clerics had been disciplined for abuse violations.
-
Original Data Provided By:
Dr Stephanie Starling, David McCandless, DM
Omid Kashan, Karl Webster
Subtitles Compiled By:
BreadCodes