Original Data Provided By:
Dr Stephanie Starling, David McCandless, DM
Omid Kashan, Karl Webster
Subtitles Compiled By:
BreadCodes
-
FALSE-ISH
Stratton Oakmont was the real name of Belfort's company, but it wasn't a Wall Street firm. It was run out of a suburban shopping mall in Long Island. Belfort trained his people to imply they were a Wall Street firm when selling stock.
FALSE
Porush claimed they did hire little people to attend a party but didn't abuse them. In the memoir, they discuss throwing little people, but it didn't happen.
TRUE
Belfort was a heavy drug user & hired a LOT of prostitutes. In an interview with Hollywood Reporter Belfort says he did more quaaludes than cocaine, but the film maximises the cocaine usage because it's more fun to watch someone snorting a line than taking a pill.
Did nearly crash his private helicopter outside his house while high on quaaludes, Xanax & morphine.
TRUE
Belfort had a major drug habit.
Belfort did take the bus to Wall Street when he first started. Recalled feeling intimidated by the city.
TRUE
Belfort recalled this in the memoir. The man was Scott, his boss, who Belfort recalled looked like a goldfish.
Belfort met Hanna in 1987 while working at L.F. Rothschild. He had been impressed by Belfort's job interview tactic - pitching stock.
TRUE
Belfort started on Wall Street May 4th, 1987. Starting making calls as a connector. Described being inspired by the roar of the office, the energy.
Hanna explained that stocks are meaningless, sold not bought, that brokers are salesmen who never stop pushing.
TRUE
Hanna did give this advice, first at the office in passing, later over lunch.
FALSE
DiCaprio & Scorsese noticed McConaughey doing it on set & decided to use it in the film. It became a sort of motif throughout the movie, with Belfort taking it with him to Stratton Oakmont.
TRUE-ISH
Although a strip club wasn't mentioned in the memoir, Belfort was known for his love of strippers.
TRUE
Passed his series 7 exam in 1987.
Black Wednesday - 19th October 1987. Stock market fell by 500 points. L.F. Rothschild did fold.
TRUE-ISH
While this particular scene was not in the book, Belfort does recall his first wife with fondness, remembering how kind & supportive she was.
TRUE
In 1988 Belfort went to work at 'Investors Center' a penny stock house. It was shut down by the SEC a year later.
TRUE-ISH
Belfort did start making his fortune by selling penny stocks.
FALSE
In the movie Belfort met Azoff in a restaurant. Azoff said if Belfort could show him a paystub for $72k, he would quit his job & work for him. Porush did work for Belfort, but in reality, Porush was introduced to Belfort by his wife, who met him on the commuter bus. They lived in the same building.
TRUE
Porush did marry his first cousin. Given all the drugs they did, it's reasonable to assume crack was on the list.
Bought a car dealership from a friend. Along with old acquaintance Kenneth Greene, set up a franchise of Stratton, later buying out Stratton & forming Stratton Oakmont.
Not in the book.
Although the memoir portrayed Denise as a good woman, this particular conversation was not recorded in the memoir.
TRUE
Belfort worked out a way to sell to the rich, tempting them with blue chip stock before pushing the high-margin rubbish.
Belfort came up with a script for his brokers to follow, proved wildly succesful.
TRUE
Stratton Oakmont was wildly succesful.
Belfort & Porush claimed somebody's head was shaved & they were given $10k. Strippers, prostitutes, & all manner of other 'services' came direct to the office.
TRUE
FBI agent Gregory Coleman was a lone ranger for years in his case against Belfort.
Forbes writer Roula Khalaf did do an article on Belfort.
FALSE
This nickname did not appear in the Forbes article. Porush does not recall anybody ever calling Belfort 'Wolf of Wall Street'.
TRUE
Belfort recalled that he had young men lining up to work for him after this.
Plenty of sex, drugs, crazed behaviour in the office. Belfort recalled testosterone-fuelled madness.
FALSE
According to Porush, office never declared 'fuck free zone'. This directly contradicts what Belfort said in the memoir.
Porush said three-way between Belfort, Azoff & a young female colleague never happened.
FALSE-ISH
Josh Shapiro, a former Strattonite who has come forward with his own account, said there was a girl who gave blowjobs to 40 Strattonites on a coach trip to Atlantic City. He dated her for a year & a half, didn't commit suicide.
TRUE
Max was the firm's chief financial officer, & notoriously tightly-wound.
The memoir dedicated three pages to this discussion.
TRUE
Mad Max described as a reserved spender from the Depression era. Can't handle the hundreds of thousands Stratton Oakmont spent on dining, prostitutes, etc.
Prostitutes at the office was a regular feature at Stratton Oakmont, mentioned again & again in the book. Belfort claims they 'classified' them like stocks, e.g. 'blue chip', 'pink sheet'.
Not in the book.
This discussion was not recorded in the memoir.
TRUE-ISH
Nadine's ex boyfriend, Alan Wilzig, has said that he introduced Nadine to Belfort at a beach party.
TRUE
Although the memoir did not discuss their early dating days, it is reasonable to assume they went out to eat at some point.
TRUE-ISH
Denise catching Belfort with Nadine was not in the memoir, but he did leave Denise for Nadine.
Belfort had a host of domestic staff, although no particular butler was described.
Not in the book.
This incident wasn't recorded in the memoir.
TRUE-ISH
Garrett acted as a rathole for Belfort.
TRUE
This did happen. One investigation fell flat on a technicality.
Belfort had the conference room bugged so he could listen in on the SEC officers, & he kept it freezing in there to get them out quicker.
TRUE
Strattong was accused of manipulating at least 34 IPOs.
TRUE-ISH
Although this moment wasn't in the memoir, they did marry.
TRUE
Not in the memoir, but given the multiple accounts of Belfort's partying it is likely that he had a stag party.
TRUE-ISH
Although this moment wasn't in the memoir, they did marry. Naomi had an Aunt Patricia.
TRUE
167-foot motor yacht, named Nadine, built for Coco Chanel & captained by the same man who flew Belfort's helicopter. Went vacationing on the yacht with friends. Did live on Long Island, in a mansion.
In the memoir Belfort was dreaming about Venice when Nadine woke him by throwing water over him in a rage, because he had been calling out Venice's name. Venice was a dominatrix.
TRUE
Apparently this was in the Presidential Suite at the Helmsley Palace.
At this point he had one daughter, Chandler. He tried to lie about Venice, claiming he was considering a project in Venice, California.
TRUE
Belfort did crash land his helicopter on his estate. The pilot had been instructed only to take over if there was imminent danger, or Belfort passed out.
FALSE
Belfort tripped & fell into the soft grass around his estate, not into the pool.
TRUE
She was furious about Venice, & angry at Belfort's attempts to sweeten her up & end the fight.
Naomi spread her legs to tease Belfort in punishment, not knowing they were being watched on cctv by the security guards.
TRUE
Porush admitted to swallowing a goldfish. Stratton Oakmont did control shares in STEVE MADDEN Ltd. Madden & Porush were childhood friends.
The FBI did take a copy of Belfort & Naomi's wedding video from Steve Burstein who shot the original.
TRUE
Belfort did hire a P.I., Richard 'Bo' Dietl, who played himself in the movie. They discussed the FBI case in an Italian restaurant in Harlem.
Not in the book.
Attempted bribery of FBI officers was not in the memoir. Although the P.I. did warn Belfort not to do it, suggesting it might have been considered.
TRUE-ISH
Belfort went to Switzerland to arrange keeping his money hidden in Swiss accounts.
TRUE
Belfort took a combination of Quaaludes & Restorils before the flight.
Belfort harassed Franca, a stewardess.
TRUE
Belfort was tied down with 4 seatbelts.
Belfort was groping the stewardess & sticking his tongue in her mouth.
TRUE
Porush had tried to stop Belfort but he had been too wild.
Belfort was questioned about his behaviour by airport security, but the stewardess dropped the charges & he went free. The sense was that Handali made the charges go away.
TRUE
Saurel not his real name - the banker was Jean Jacques Handali. Handali came out to meet them as they stepped off the elevator.
There was a meeting like this.
FALSE
Handali & Belfort hit it off & there didn't seem to be any power struggle there.
TRUE
Nadine had an English Aunt Patricia. She smuggled money into Switzerland for Belfort, & put it into an account opened in her name. She was to live off the account for the rest of her life. They met & discussed the deal in Hyde Park just as in the film.
FALSE
There was no kiss. In the memoir, Belfort poured his heart out to her, & the reader was shown his vulnerabilities.
TRUE
According to the memoir it was $3million.
TRUE-ISH
Porush claims this didn't happen, but according to the memoir it did happen but Porush wasn't present. Belfort did have a friend, Garret, (his drug-dealer) with a Swiss wife, Carolyn, who, along with her family, smuggled cash for Belfort. The memoir recalled the taping incident. Belfort told Garret to meet Porush to collect $1m cash, & Garret insisted that Porush turn up sober & not be an ass.
FALSE
Porush wasn't there.
TRUE
Nadine's mother Suzanne & her Aunt Patricia, along with Chantalle & her family (including Garret's parents), all smuggled cash into Switzerland.
TRUE-ISH
Porush turned up actually stoned (not faking it like in the movie), in a flashy Rolls Royce, to meet Garret in a shopping centre car park.
FALSE-ISH
Apparently Garret threatened to kill Porush for turning up stoned, so Porush left quickly.
TRUE
The security guards thought Porush was drink-driving & called the police. Porush handed the cash over & left. Police turned up & arrested Garret before he could get away, thinking it was a drug deal. Ended up being held on possession of a firearm charges.
FALSE-ISH
Porush didn't know Garret had been arrested & assured Belfort that it all went fine. The ancient top strength quaaludes, Lemmon 714, did feature in the book. Belfort was offered a supply when a retired pharmacist decided to sell them off to pay his kid's tuition.
TRUE
Belfort described having an enema & making himself vomit to clear his system for the special quaaludes.
Belfort & Porush took several of the Lemmon 714s together at his house, while working out in the gym. Waiting for them to kick in. Despite being warned only to take one.
TRUE-ISH
Belfort got a call from his P.I. Bo Dietl, who had info on the FBI case. Told him to go to a payphone & call him back. However, the call came through his assistant Gwynne, not Nadine.m
Belfort found out from Carolyn, not the P.I., that Garret had been arrested because of Porush. Belfort did phone his P.I. from the country club payphone, where he was told that the FBI were onto the $20m he had in Swiss accounts & that Belfort's home phones were tapped.
TRUE
At this point the quaaludes set in & he could barely speak or walk. After years in storage they had developed a long fuse.
FALSE
Nadine didn't phone him, but he realised Nadine would see Porush in the same state & freak out, panicked, wanted to get home asap.
TRUE
Belfort did drive home totally wasted.
Not in the book.
This didn't feature in the memoir.
TRUE
Belfort did think he made it home without damanging himself, the car, or anyone else.
FALSE
Belfort didn't see or interact with Porush when he arrived home. Nadine, crying, kissed him, begged him to take better care of himself. Rocco & Rocco escorted him to bed.
FALSE-ISH
Belfort didn't save Azoff from choking, but he did save a different man from the same fate during a period that was cut from the film. He did think twice about administering CPR, the guy was 'evil'. But his conscience & the screaming people around him pushed him to act.
TRUE
The police woke Belfort & arrested him for driving under the influence, reckless endangerment, & leaving the scene of an accident.
He had caused 7 accidents on the way home from the country club. The car was totally wrecked.
FALSE-ISH
Car was not a Lamborghini but a Mercedes, according to Belfort. Did drive it home wasted. Not true that nobody was hurt - a head-on collision landed a woman in hospital with a broken arm.
TRUE
They couldn't prove he was intoxicated while driving. His lawyer got him out of spending the night in a cell by calling in a favour from a judge.
FALSE
Initially Garret wouldn't cooperate. However, he needed a heart transplant after contracting a virus in Brazil that caused a heart defect. The FBI pointed out that inmates don't get heart transplants, & he agreed to give info on Belfort.
TRUE-ISH
This conversation did happen, but between Belfort & his lawyer only, & in his lawyer's office. However, elsewhere in the book it was shown that Naomi was an equestrian & took their daughter riding.
FALSE-ISH
Belfort did step down. When he gave his final speech, however, he was indeed met with cheers & adoration.
FALSE
Belfort did step down.
No info on Garret's level of aliveness.
According to the memoir Garret got a heart transplant. There seems to be no reliable information on whether Garret is alive or dead. Google searches show up with 'some results may have been removed under data protection law'.
TRUE
14 Strattonites were subpoenaed. Porush was left in charge of Stratton when Belfort stepped down, & had taken to pissing on NSD subpoenas to 'thunderous applause'.
FALSE-ISH
Of the 14 questioned, two cracked. Those two were banned from the industry while the other 12 just carried on as before.
TRUE
Steve Madden did unload his shares before the decline. Ultimately Madden was sentenced to 31 months in prison, & made to resign as CEO of Steve Madden Ltd.
Aunt Patricia did die while Swiss accounts were still open.
TRUE-ISH
Belfort did order captain Captain Marc to sail, despite choppy waters. However, it wasn't to get to Switzerland in an emergency. Belfort, Nadine & friends were on holiday in Italy. Belfort, high, insisted on sailing to Sardinia.
TRUE
The yacht did sink off the coast off Sardinia during a storm. Captain Marc called Mayday, Italian coastguard came to the rescue & all on board were airlifted onto an Italian naval ship.
They did party on the Italian naval ship that took them back to land.
TRUE-ISH
While Belfort did not see his plane crash over the ocean, his private jet did crash some days later on the way to fly his group back to the States from Italy. A seagull was caught in the engine.
FALSE-ISH
Coleman did arrest Belfort, but not during his filming of an infomercial.
TRUE
Belfort attended The Talbot Marsh Recovery Campus in Atlanta, Georgia. Did go on to become a TV personality.
Handali arrested while visiting clients in Miami.
TRUE
Handali arrested for connection with laundering drug money through offshore boat racing.
Not in the book.
No mention of a restaurant chain involved in criminal activities in the book. However, the Strattonites did frequent a sushi place called Tenjin.
TRUE
Handali cooporated with the FBI against Belfort & his gang. Chantalle had been sleeping with Handali each time she dropped off cash in Switzerland, which meant he knew her personally, & could provide her name. Coleman has threatened to arrest Chantalle.
Bail was set at $10m, which he paid in the form of jewels. It took a further five years until he was put in jail.
Not in the book.
The memoir doesn't detail any such visit, in fact is doesn't really they were particularly good friends at all. Plus Porush was also under house arrest.
TRUE-ISH
Belfort was placed under house arrest following his indictment.
FALSE
The memoir didn't portray Belfort & Porush as having much of a friendship, & Porush didn't turn up to help financially in the book.
TRUE
Belfort attended rehab & was sober for a while.
Belfort agreed to rat on everybody he had ever had dealings with in return for less jail time & immunity for his wife.
TRUE
Nadine said she was leaving & taking the kids. Belfort grabbed his 3yr old, Nadine tried to stop him & he kicked her in the stomach. He did crash his car through the garage door & into a wall with his daughter inside. He was arrested and given a restraining order.
Belfort did have to wear a wire, although having the FBI agent attach it to him was artistic license.
TRUE
Belfort did rat out Porush & others for a reduced sentence & immunity for Nadine.
TRUE-ISH
By the time Belfort was finally indicted by the FBI he had long been out of Stratton Oakmont. However, he did have to meet people wearing a wire; this could easily have been in the old offices. Not clear in the book.
FALSE-ISH
Belfort recalls that he did not pass such a note to Porush, but did do this for his friend Dave Beall.
TRUE-ISH
Belfort was at home when the FBI turned up, but not in bed.
TRUE
The FBI caught Belfort as he headed off to take his daughter to Blockbuster, just outside his house.
20 or so FBI agents turned up & Belfort knew he was going to jail.
TRUE-ISH
Although we didn't see this happening to Porush in the memoir, he was indicted by the FBI.
TRUE
The original Forbes article on Belfort from 1991 stated, 'Belfort's brat-pack brokers quickly came to idolize him'. Belfort describes a 'sea of humanity...parted this way & that as they cleared a path for me...offered me a wink or a smile'.
TRUE-ISH
Sentenced to four years in prison, served 22 months.
TRUE
Coleman did finally get Belfort, after years of working by himself on the case when his colleagues said it was a lost cause.
FALSE
Belfort walked into the institution to self-surrender.
TRUE
Belfort's & his cellmate, Tommy Chong, have described their prison experience as comfortable, pleasant, with great food, tennis, & socialising.
Belfort is a highly succesful motivational speaker & consultant. Clients include Delta & Virgin Airlines.
-
Original Data Provided By:
Dr Stephanie Starling, David McCandless, DM
Omid Kashan, Karl Webster
Subtitles Compiled By:
BreadCodes